<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An answer to Monsieur de la Militiere his impertinent dedication of his imaginary triumph, to the king of Great Britain to invite him to embrace the Roman Catholick religion. / By John Bramhall D.D. and Lord Bishop of London-Derry.</title>
            <author>Bramhall, John, 1594-1663.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1653</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 173 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 118 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A74667</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1542_1</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">50796707</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 50796707</idno>
            <idno type="VID">170067</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A74667)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 170067)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 195:E1542[1])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An answer to Monsieur de la Militiere his impertinent dedication of his imaginary triumph, to the king of Great Britain to invite him to embrace the Roman Catholick religion. / By John Bramhall D.D. and Lord Bishop of London-Derry.</title>
                  <author>Bramhall, John, 1594-1663.</author>
                  <author>La Milletière, Théophile Brachet, sieur de, ca. 1596-1665. Victory of truth for the peace of the Church.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 226 [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Hague, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the year, 1653.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>La Milletière, Théophile Brachet, --  sieur de, ca. 1596-1665. --  Victory of truth for the peace of the Church.</term>
               <term>Church of England --  Relations --  Catholic Church.</term>
               <term>Catholic Church --  Relations --  Church of England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:170067:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN ANSWER TO Monſeiur de la Militiere his impertinent Dedica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his Imaginary Triumph, To the KING of Great <hi>Britain,</hi> to invite him to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace the Roman Catholick Religion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> John Bramhall <hi>D. D. and Lord Biſhop of</hi> Derry.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>HAGUE,</hi> Printed in the Year, 1653.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:170067:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:170067:2"/>
            <head>An Anſwer to Monſeiur <hi>de la Militiere</hi> his Epiſtle to the King of great <hi>Britain,</hi> wherein he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viteth his Majeſty to forſake the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace the Roman Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Religion.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Ou might long have diſputed your Queſtion of Tranſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiation, with your learned Adverſary, and proclamed your own Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:170067:3"/>
on a ſilver Trumpet to the world, before any Member of the Church of <hi>England</hi> had interpoſed in this preſent Exigence of our Affairs. I know no neceſſity that Chriſtians muſt be like Cocks,<note place="margin">Plut.</note> that <hi>when one Crows all the reſt muſt Crow for Company.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Monſeiur Aubertine</hi> will not want a ſurviving friend, to teach you what it is to ſound a Triumph before you have gained the victory. He was no fool that deſired no other Epitaph on his Tomb than this, Here lyes the Author of this ſentence, <hi>Prurigo Diſputandi ſcabies Eccleſiae,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Sir</hi> Henry Wotton.</note> the itch of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puting is the ſcab of the Church.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:170067:3"/>Having viewed all your ſtrength with a ſingle eye, I find not one of your Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments that comes home to Tranſubſtantiation, but only to a true reall preſence, which no genuine Son of the Church of <hi>England</hi> did ever deny, no nor your Adverſary himſelf. Chriſt ſaid, <hi>This is my Body,</hi> what he ſaid, we do ſtedfaſtly believe; he ſaid not, after this or that man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, <hi>neque con, neque ſub, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que trans;</hi> And therefore we place it among the Opinions of the Schools, not among the Articles of our Faith.</p>
            <p>The holy Euchariſt, which is the Sacrament of peace and unity,<note place="margin">rences in the Church directly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the Sacrament for the firſt 800. years.</note> ought not to be made the matter of ſtrife and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention. There wanted not
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:170067:4"/>
abuſes in the Adminiſtration of this Sacrament, in the moſt pure and Primitive times, as prophaneſs and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charitableneſs among the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinthians.<note place="margin">1 Cor. 11.</note> The Simonians and Menandrians, and ſome other ſuch Imps of Sathan, unworthy the name of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians,<note place="margin">Theod. ex Ignatio.</note> did wholy forbear the uſe of the Euchariſt, but it was not for any difference a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the Sacrament it ſelf, but about the naturall Body of Chriſt; <hi>They held that his fleſh, and Blood, and Paſſion, were not true and reall, but imaginary and phantasticall things.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Maniches did forbear the Cup, but it was not for any difference about the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament it ſelf; They made
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:170067:4"/>
two Gods, a good God whom they called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> or light, and an evill God whom they tearmed <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> or darkneſs, which evill God (they ſaid,) did make ſome creatures of the Dreg, or more feculent parts of the matter, which were evill and impure; And among theſe evill creatures they eſteemed Wine, which they called the Gall of the Dragon: for this cauſe, not upon any other ſcruple, they either wholy abſteined from the Cup,<note place="margin">Leo. Ser. <hi>4.</hi> de quad. Epiph. haer. <hi>30.</hi> &amp; <hi>46.</hi>
               </note> or uſed Water in the place of wine, which <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piphanius</hi> recordeth among the errors of the <hi>Ebionites,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. li. de Haereſ. c. <hi>64</hi>
               </note> and <hi>Tacians;</hi> And St. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine</hi> of the <hi>Aquarians.</hi> Still we doe not find any claſhing either in word or writing
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:170067:5"/>
directly about this Sacrament, in the univerſall Church of Chriſt, much leſs about the preſence of Chriſt in the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament.<note place="margin">Bel. l. <hi>1.</hi> de Sac. Euch. c. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Neque ullus vete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum diſputat contra hunc er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rorem primis ſex centis An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The firſt that are ſuppoſed by <hi>Bellarmine</hi> to have broa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched any error in the Church about the reall preſence were the <hi>Iconomachi,</hi> after 700. years. <hi>Primi qui veritatem corporis Domini in Euchari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtia in quaeſtionem vecarunt fuerint Iconomachi poſt An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num Domini</hi> 700.<note place="margin">Bel ibid. Syn Nic. <hi>2</hi> Act <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> only be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they called the Bread and Wine the Image of Chriſts body. This is as great a miſtake as the former. Their difference was meerly
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:170067:5"/>
about Images, not at all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the Euchariſt; ſo much <hi>Vaſques</hi> confeſſeth,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Diſp.</hi> 179. <hi>c.</hi> 1.</note> that <hi>In his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>udgement they are not to be numbred with thoſe who deny the preſence of Chriſt in the Euchariſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We may well find different obſervations in thoſe dayes,<note place="margin">Yet diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent ob<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſervations,</note> as one Church conſecrating leavened Bread, another un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leavened; One Church ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king uſe of pure Wine, ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of Wine mixed with Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; One Church admitting Infants to the Communion, another not admitting them; but without controverſies, or cenſures, or animoſity one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt another: we find no debates or diſputes concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the preſence of Chriſts Body in the Sacrament, and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:170067:6"/>
much leſs concerning the manner of his preſence, for the firſt eight hundred years.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">And diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions.</note>Yet all the time we find as different expreſſions among thoſe Primitive Fathers, as among our modern writers at this day, ſome calling the Sacrament <hi>the ſign of Chriſts Body, the figure of his Body, the Symbol of his Body, the myſtery of his Body, the exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plar type and repreſentation of his Body, ſaying that the Elements do not recede from their firſt nature;</hi> others na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming it <hi>the true Body and Blood of Chriſt, changed not in ſhape but in nature,</hi> yea doubting not to ſay, that in this Sacrament <hi>we ſee Chriſt, we touch Chriſt, we eat Chriſt, that we faſten our teeth in
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:170067:6"/>
his very fleſh, and make our Tongues red in his Bloud:</hi> Yet notwithanſting there were no queſtions, no quarrels, no contentions amongſt them; there needed no Councils to order them, no conferences to reconcile them, becauſe they contented themſelves to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve what Chriſt had ſaid, <hi>This is my Body,</hi> without preſuming upon their own heads, to determine the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner how it is his Body, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther weighing all their own words ſo exactly before any controverſie was raiſed, nor expounding the ſayings of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther men contrary to the ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy of Faith.</p>
            <p>The firſt doubt about the<note place="margin">The firſt difference abou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the preſence of Chriſt in the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament.</note> preſence of Chriſts Body in the Sacrament ſeems to have
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:170067:7"/>
been moved not long before the year 900. in the dayes of <hi>Bertram,</hi> and <hi>Paſchaſius,</hi> but the controverſie was not well formed, nor this new Article of Tranſubſtantiation ſufficiently concocted in the dayes of <hi>Berengarius,</hi> after the year 1050. as appeareth by the groſs miſtaking, and mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtating of the queſtion on both ſides; Firſt <hi>Berengarius</hi> (if we may truſt his adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries) knew no mean between a naked figure, or empty ſign of Chriſts preſence, and a corporeall or Locall preſence, and afterwards fell into a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother extreme of <hi>impanation;</hi> on the other ſide the Pope and the Councill made no diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence between Conſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiation and Tranſubſtantia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:170067:7"/>
they underſtood nothing of the ſpirituall or indiviſible being of the fleſh and blood of Chriſt in the Sacrament, as appeareth by that ignorant and Capernaiticall retractati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and abjuration, which they impoſed upon <hi>Berengarius,</hi> Penned by <hi>Umbertus</hi> a Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinall,<note place="margin">Exact. Syn. Rom. ſub Nich. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> approved by Pope <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cholas,</hi> and a Councill, <hi>Ego Berengarius,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Berengarius <hi>do conſent to the holy Roman Apostolick See, and profeſs with my mouth and heart, to hold the ſame faith of the Sacrament, of the Lords Supper, with Pope</hi> Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cholas <hi>and this holy Synod, &amp;c.</hi> And what the faith of Pope <hi>Nicholas</hi> and this Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nod was, follows in the next words; <hi>That the Bread and
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:170067:8"/>
Wine which are ſet upon the Altar after Conſecration, are not onely the Sacrament, but the very body and blood of Christ.</hi> This ſeems to favour Conſubſtantiation, rather than Tranſubſtantiation; if the Bread and Wine be the body and blood of Chriſt, then they remain Bread and Wine ſtill; if the bread be not onely the Sacrament, but alſo the thing of the Sacrament, if it be both the Sign and the thing ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, how is it now to be made nothing? It follows in the Retraction; <hi>That the body and blood of Chriſt is ſenſibly, not onely in the Sacrament, but in truth, handled and broken by the hands of the Prieſt, and bruiſed by the teeth of the faithfull,</hi> If it be even ſo,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:170067:8"/>
there needs no more but feel and be ſatisfied. To this they made <hi>Berengarius</hi> ſweat, <hi>By the conſubſtantiall Trinity, and the Holy Goſpels,</hi> and accurſe and anathematize all thoſe who held the contrary; yet theſe words did ſo much ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalize and offend the Gloſſer upon <hi>Gratian,</hi> that he could not forbear to admoniſh the Reader,<note place="margin">De Conſ. diſt. <hi>2</hi> cap. Ego Ber.</note> that <hi>unleſs he under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood thoſe words in a ſound ſenſe, he would fall into a greater hereſie than that of Berengarius.</hi> Not without reaſon, for the moſt favoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of the Schoolmen do con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs, that theſe words are not properly and literally true, but figuratively and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tanimically, underſtanding the thing conteining by the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:170067:9"/>
thing conteined, as to ſay the body of Chriſt is broken or bruiſed, becauſe the quantity or <hi>Species</hi> of bread are broken or bruiſed, they might as well ſay, that the body and blood of Chriſt becomes fuſty and ſowr, as often as the <hi>Species</hi> of Bread and Wine before their corruption become fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty and ſowr. But the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tractation of <hi>Berongarius</hi> can admit no ſuch figurative ſenſe, that <hi>the body and blood of Christ in the Sacrament are d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>vided and bruiſed ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly not onely in the Sacrament,</hi> (that is in the <hi>Spec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>es</hi>) but alſo in truth. A moſt igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant Capernaiticall aſſertion; for the body of Chriſt being not in the Sacrament <hi>modo Quantitativo,</hi> according to
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:170067:9"/>
their own <hi>Tenet,</hi> but indiviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, after a Spirituall manner, without extrinſecall extenſion of parts, cannot in it ſelf or in truth be either divided or bruiſed.</p>
            <p>Therefore others of the School-men goe more roundly and ingenuouſly to work,<note place="margin">Alex. Gab. Bonav. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> and confeſs that <hi>it is an abuſive and exceſſive expreſſion, not to be held or defended,</hi> &amp; that <hi>it hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened to</hi> Berengarius, (they ſhould have ſaid to Pope <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cholas,</hi> and Cardinall <hi>Umber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus,) as it doth with thoſe who cut of a deteſtation of one er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror encline to another.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Neither will it a vail them any thing at all, that the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers have ſometimes uſed ſuch expreſſions of <hi>ſeeing Chriſt,</hi> of <hi>touching Chriſt</hi> in the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:170067:10"/>
of <hi>faſtning our teeth in his fleſh,</hi> and <hi>making our tongues red in his blood.</hi> There is a great difference between a Sermon to the people, and a ſolemn Retractation before a Judge. The Fathers do not ſay, that ſuch expreſſions are true, not only Sacramentally or figuratively, (as they made <hi>Berengarius</hi> both ſay and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſe all others that held o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe) but alſo properly, and in the things themſelves. The Fathers never meant by theſe forms of ſpeech, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine the manner of the preſence, (which was not dreamed of in their dayes) but to raiſe the devotion of their hearers and readers, to advertiſe the people of God, that they ſhould not reſt in
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:170067:10"/>
the externall ſymbols, or ſigns, but principa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ly be intent upon the inviſible grace, which was both lawfull and commendable for them to do. Leave us their primitive liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and we will not refrain from the like expreſſions.</p>
            <p>I urge this to ſhew that the new doctrine of Tranſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiation is ſo far from being an old Article of faith, that it was not well digeſted, not rightly underſtood, in any tollerable meaſure, by the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt Clerks, and moſt concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, above a thouſand years after Chriſt.</p>
            <p>The firſt definition or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termination of this manner of the preſence was yet later in the Councill of <hi>Lateran,</hi> in the dayes of <hi>Innocent</hi> the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:170067:11"/>
third,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Scot. in</hi> 4. <hi>ſent. diſt.</hi> 11. <hi>q.</hi> 3. <hi>T.</hi> 3 <hi>q.</hi> 75. <hi>d.</hi> 81. <hi>c.</hi> 1. The deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination of the manner of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned a floodgate to a deluge of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſies.</note> after the year 1200. <hi>Ante Lateranenſe Concilium Tranſubſtantiatio non fuit dogma fidei.</hi> And what the fruit of it was, let <hi>Vaſques</hi> bear witneſs, <hi>Audito nomine Tranſubſtantiationis,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>The very name of Tranſubſtantia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion being but heard, ſo great a Controverſie d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d ariſe among the later School-men concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the nature thereof, that the more they endevoured to wind themſelves out, the more they wrapped themſelves in greater difficulties, whereby the mysterie of faith became more difficult, both to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained, and to be understood, and more expoſed to the Cavils of its Adverſaries.</hi> He adds that the <hi>name of Converſion and Tranſubſtantiation gave
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:170067:11"/>
occaſion to theſe Controverſies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>No ſooner was this Bell rung out, no ſooner was this fatall ſentence given, but as if <hi>Pandora</hi>'s box had been newly ſet wide open, whole ſwarms of noiſome Queſtions and debates did fill the Schools. Then it began to be diſputed by what means this change comes, whether by the Benediction of the Elements, or by the Repetition of theſe words of Chriſt, <hi>This is my body.</hi> The common current of your Schools is for the later:<note place="margin">Lib. de Corr. Theol. Schol.</note> But your judicious Arch-Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops of <hi>Caeſaria,</hi> ſince the Councill of <hi>Trent,</hi> in a Book dedicated to <hi>Sixtus</hi> the Fifth, produceth great reaſons to the contrary.</p>
            <p>Then was the Queſtion ſtar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:170067:12"/>
what the demonſtrative Pronoun <hi>Hoc</hi> ſignifies in theſe words, <hi>This is my Body;</hi> whether this thing, or this Subſtance, or this Bread, or this Body, or this Meat, or theſe Accidents, or that which is conteined under theſe <hi>Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gloſs. de Con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>. d. <hi>2.</hi> cap. timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem.</note> or this <hi>Individuum va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gum,</hi> or laſtly (which ſeems ſtranger than all the reſt) this Nothing.</p>
            <p>Then it began to be argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, whether the Elements were annihilated; whether the matter and form of them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing deſtroyed their eſſence did yet remain, or the eſſence be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Converted the exiſtence remained; whether the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall exiſtence of the body and blood of Chriſt do de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend upon its naturall exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtence;
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:170067:12"/>
whether the whole Hoſt were Tranſubſtantiated, or onely ſome parts of it, that is ſuch parts as ſhould be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtributed to worthy Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicants, or whether in thoſe parts of the Hoſt which were diſtributed unto unworthy Communicants the matter of Bread and Wine did not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn.<note place="margin">Guidmend. l. <hi>1.</hi> de ver.</note> Whether the Deity did aſſume the Bread or the <hi>Species</hi> thereof, by a new Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtaticall Union, called <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panation,</hi> either abſolutely, or reſpectively <hi>Mediante Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pore.</hi> Whether the body and blood of Chriſt might be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent in the Sacrament with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Tranſubſtantiation, with the bread, or without the bread; whether a body may be tranſubſtantiated into a
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:170067:13"/>
Spirit,<note place="margin">Vaſq. diſp. <hi>184.</hi> c. <hi>8.</hi>
               </note> and (which is moſt ſtrange) whether a Creature might be tranſubſtantiated in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Deity.</p>
            <p>Then the School-men be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to wrangle what manner of change this was, whether a material change, or a formall change, or a change of the whole ſubſtance, both matter and form; And if it were a Converſion of the whole ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, then whether it was by way of Production, or by Adduction, or by Conſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, each of which greater Squadrons are ſubdivided into ſeverall leſſer parties, ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as different Language, as the builders of <hi>Babel,</hi> peſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and perplexing one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with mextricable diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:170067:13"/>It cannot be a new Produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction (ſaith one) becauſe the body of Chriſt, whereinto the Elements are ſuppoſed to be converted, did pre-exiſt before the change, neither can that body which is made of bread, be the ſame body with that which was born of a Virgin.</p>
            <p>If it be not by Production (ſay others,) but onely by Adduction, then it is not a Tranſubſtantiation, but a Tran-ſubiation, not a change of natures, but a locall ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. Then the Prieſt is not the Maker of his Maker, (as they uſe to brag,) but onely puts him into a new poſiture, or preſence, under the <hi>Species</hi> of Bread and Wine.</p>
            <p>Howbeit this way by Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction be the more common,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:170067:14"/>
and the ſafer way (if we may truſt <hi>Bellarmine</hi>) yet of all Converſions or changes, it hath leaſt affinity with Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantiation. Suppoſe the Water had not been turned into Wine at <hi>Cana</hi> of <hi>Gallilee</hi> by our Saviour, but poured out, or utterly deſtroyed, and Wine new created, or ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced by Miracle into the water-pots, in ſuch a manner, that the introduction of the Wine ſhould be the expulſion of the Water, not onely <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitanter,</hi> but <hi>Cauſaliter,</hi> in ſuch caſe it had been no Tranſubſtantiation. <hi>Moſes</hi> his Rod was truly changed into a Serpent, but it was by Production, if his Rod had been conveyed away inviſibly, by Legerdemain, and a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:170067:14"/>
had been adduced into the place of it, what Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantiation had this been? None at all; no, though the adduction of the Serpent had been the means of the expulſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and deſtruction of the Rod. It is ſo far from Tranſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiation, that is no Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion at all. The ſubſtance of the Elements is not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted, for that is ſuppoſed to be deſtroyed; The Accidents are not converted, but remain the ſame they were. It is no Adduction at all, when the body of Chriſt (which is the thing ſuppoſed to be adduced) remains ſtill in Heaven, where it was before.</p>
            <p>It cannot be a Conſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive converſion, (ſay others,) for the ſame individuall thing
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:170067:15"/>
cannot be conſerved by two totall diſtinct Conſervations; but if this were a conſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive converſion the body of Chriſt ſhould be conſerved by two totall diſtinct conſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, the one in Heaven, the other in Earth; Yea, by ten thouſand diſtinct totall Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervations upon Eatth, even as many as there are conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Hoſts;<note place="margin">
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>aſq. T. <hi>3.</hi> q. <hi>75.</hi> d. <hi>181</hi> c. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Which ſeems to be ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diculous, and without any neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity adminiſters great occaſion to the Adverſaries of Chriſtian Religion, of jeaſting and deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the myſteries of our faith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So here we have a Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantiation without tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantiation; A production of a <hi>Modus</hi> or manner of Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, for a production of a ſubſtance; An Annihilation
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:170067:15"/>
ſuppoſed, yet no Annihilation confeſſed; an Adduction with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any Adduction; a <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minus ad Quem,</hi> without a <hi>Terminus à quo;</hi> who ſhall reconcile us to our ſelves? But the end is not yet.</p>
            <p>Then grew up the Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, What is the proper Ade<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quate body which is contei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned under the <hi>Species</hi> or ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidents; Whether a materiall body, or a ſubſtantiall body, or a living body, or an Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganicall body, or an humane body; Whether it have weight, or not, and why it is not perceived; Whether it can be ſeen by the eye of mortall man; whether it can act or ſuffer any thing, whether it be moveable or immovable; whether by it ſelf, or by Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:170067:16"/>
or by both; whether it can move in one place, and reſt in another; or be moved with two contrary motions, (as upwards and downwards, Southwards and North<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards,) at the ſame time?</p>
            <p>Add to theſe, whether the Soul of Chriſt, and the Deity, and the whole Trinity do fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low the body and blood of Chriſt under either <hi>Species,</hi> by Concomitance? Whether the Sacramentall body muſt have ſuffered the ſame things with the naturall body? As ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing that an Hoſt Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crated at Chriſts laſt Supper had been reſerved untill after his Paſſion, whether Chriſt muſt have died, and his blood have been actually ſhed in the Sacrament? Yea, whether
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:170067:16"/>
thoſe wounds which were im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>printed by the whips in his naturall body, might and ſhould have been found in his Sacramentall body with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out flagellation?</p>
            <p>Likewiſe, what blood of Chriſt is in the Sacrament? whether that blood onely which was ſhed, or that blood only which remained in the body, or both the one and the other? And whether that blood which was ſhed was aſſumed again by the Humanity in the Reſurrection?</p>
            <p>Then began thoſe Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doxicall Queſtions to be firſt agitated in the Schools, Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the ſame individuall bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, without diviſion, or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>continuation from it ſelf, can be locally in ten thouſand places; yea, in Heaven and in
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:170067:17"/>
Earth at the ſame time; Or if not locally, yet whether it can be ſo ſpiritually, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diviſibly? And whether it be not the ſame as to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, whether a body be lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>locally or ſpiritually preſent in more places than one? <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmine</hi> ſeems to incline to the affirmative.<note place="margin">Bell. l. <hi>3.</hi> de Euch. c. <hi>3.</hi> in fine.</note> 
               <hi>Though to be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny where Sacramentally doth not imply the taking up of a place, yet it implies a true and reall preſence, and if it be in more Hoſts or Altars than one, it ſeems no leſs oppoſite unto Indiviſibility, than the filling up of many places.</hi> Nay, he is paſt ſeeming poſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, <hi>that, without doubt if a body cannot be in two places locally, it cannot be Sacramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally in two places.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:170067:17"/>Compare this of <hi>Bellarmine</hi> with that of <hi>Aquinas,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>In</hi> 4. <hi>d.</hi> 44. <hi>q.</hi> 7. <hi>art.</hi> 2. <hi>q.</hi> 3.</note> that <hi>it is not poſſible for one body to be in more places than one locally, no not by Miracle, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it implies a contradicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;</hi> And conſider upon what tottering foundations you build Articles of faith. It is impoſſible, and implies a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction, for the body of Chriſt to be locally in more Hoſts than one at the ſame time (ſaith <hi>Aquinas,</hi>) But it is as impoſſible, and implies a Contradiction aſmuch for the body of Chriſt to be Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentally in more Hoſts than one at the ſame time, as to be locally (ſaith <hi>Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine</hi>). The Inference is plain and obvious.</p>
            <p>Many more ſuch ſtrange
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:170067:18"/>
Queſtions are moved, as whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be poſſible that the thing conteined ſhould be a thouſand times greater than the thing conteining? whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a definitive being in a place, do not implie a not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out of that place? whether more bodies than one can be in one and the ſame place? whether there can be a pene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tration of dimenſions? whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a body can ſubſiſt after a ſpirituall manner, ſo as to take up no place at all, but to be wholly in the whole, and wholly in every part? More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, whether the whole bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and blood of Chriſt be in every particle of the bread, and of the Cup, and if it be, then whether onely after the diviſion of the Bread and
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:170067:18"/>
Wine, or before diviſion alſo; And in how many parts, and in which parts, is the whole body and blood of Chriſt, whether in the leaſt parts, and if in the leaſt parts, then whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the leaſt in kind, or the leaſt in quantity, that is ſo long as the <hi>Species</hi> may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tein the name of Bread and Wine, or ſo long as the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is diviſible, and whether the body and blood of Chriſt, be alſo in the indiviſible parts, as points and lines, and ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perficies?</p>
            <p>Laſtly, whether Accidents can ſubſiſt without their ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, that is, whether they can be both Accidents, and no Accidents? whether all the Accidents of the Elements do remain, and particularly
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:170067:19"/>
whether the Quantity doth remain? whether the other Accidents do inhere in the quantity as their ſubject, that is, whether an Accident can have an Accident? whether the quantity of Chriſts body be there, and whether it be there after a quantitative man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, with extenſion of parts, either extrinſecall or intrinſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call, and whether the Quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity of the body of Chriſt, be diſtinct and figured, or indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct and unfigured? whether the Accidents can nouriſh or make drunken, or corrupt, and a new body be generated of them; And what ſupplies the place of the matter in ſuch generation, whether the Quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity, or the body of Chriſt, or the old matter of the Bread
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:170067:19"/>
and wine, reſtored by mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle, or new matter created by God? And how long in ſuch corruption the Body of Chriſt doth continue.</p>
            <p>Whoſoever is but mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rately verſed in your great Doctors, muſt needs know that theſe queſtions are not the private doubts, or debates of ſingle School-men, but the common Garboils and generall engagements of your whole Schools.</p>
            <p>Wherefore it had been a meer vanity to cite every par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Author for each que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, and would have made the margent ſwell ten times greater than the Text.</p>
            <p>From this bold determina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the manner of the preſence, how, have flowed
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:170067:20"/>
two other differences, Firſt the detention of the Cup from the Laity, meerly upon pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption of Concomitance, firſt decreed in the Councill of <hi>Conſtance,</hi> after the year 1400. Let what will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of Concomitance, whilſt we keep our ſelves to the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of Chriſt, and the univerſall practiſe of the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Church. It was not for nothing that our Saviour did diſtinguiſh his Body from his Bloud, not only in the Conſecration, but alſo in the diſtribution of the Sacrament. By the way give me leave to repreſent a Contradiction in <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> which I am not able to reconcile.<note place="margin">Lib. <hi>4.</hi> de Euch. c. <hi>25.</hi>
               </note> In one place he ſaith, <hi>The provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of God is merveilous in
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:170067:20"/>
holy Scripture, for St.</hi> Luke <hi>hath put theſe words [do you this,] after the Sacrament given under the form of Bread, but he repeated it not after the giving of the Cup, That we might understand, that the Lord commanded that the Sacrament ſhould be distri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted unto all under the form of Bread, but not under the form of Wine.</hi> And yet in the next Chapter but one of the ſame Book, he doth poſitive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly determine the contrary, upon the Ground of Conco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitance, that <hi>the Bread may be taken away,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cap. 27.</note> 
               <hi>if the Cup be given, but both cannot be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away together,</hi> Can that be taken away, which Chriſt hath expreſly commanded to be given to all?</p>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:170067:21"/>A ſecond difference flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from Tranſubſtantiation is about the Adoration of the Sacrament; One of thoſe im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pediments which hinder our Communication with you in the Celebration of divine Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices: We deny not a <hi>vene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable reſpect</hi> unto the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrate Elements, not only as love-tokens ſent us by our beſt friend, but as the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments ordeined by our Saviour to convey to us the merits of his Paſſion: But for the perſon of Chriſt (God forbid) that we ſhould deny him divine worſhip at any time, and eſpecially in the uſe of this holy Sacrament, we beleeve with St. <hi>Auſtine</hi> that <hi>No man eats of that fleſh, but firſt he adores.</hi> But
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:170067:21"/>
that which offends us is this, That you teach and require all men to adore the very Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament with divine Honour. To this end you hold it out to the people. To this end <hi>Corpus Christi</hi> day was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted about 300. years ſince.<note place="margin">Conc. Vien.</note> Yet we know that even up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on your own grounds, you cannot without a particular Revelation, have any infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible aſſurance that any <hi>Hoſt</hi> is conſecrated; And conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently you have no aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance that you do not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit materiall Idolatry.</p>
               <p>But that which weighs moſt with us is this, That we dare not give divine wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip unto any creature, (no not to the very Humanity of Chriſt in the Abſtract, much
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:170067:22"/>
leſs to the Hoſt) but to the whole perſon of Chriſt God and man, by reaſon of the Hypoſtaticall union between the Child of the bleſſed Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin <hi>Mary,</hi> and the eternall Son, <hi>who is God over all bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed for ever.</hi> Shew us ſuch an union betwixt the Deity and the Elements, or accidents, and you ſay ſomething. But you pretend no ſuch things, The higheſt that you dare go is this,<note place="margin">Bell. l. <hi>4</hi> de Euch. c. <hi>29.</hi> quodam modo.</note> 
                  <hi>As they that adored Chriſt when hee was upon Earth did [after a certain kind of manner,] adore his Garments.</hi> Is this all? This is <hi>after a certain kind of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner indeed.</hi> We have enough. There is no more Adoration due to the Sacrament, than to the Garments which
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:170067:22"/>
Chriſt did wear upon Earth. Exact no more.</p>
               <p>Thus the ſeamleſs Coat of Chriſt is torn into pieces; Thus faith is minced into ſhreds, and ſpun up into ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cities, more ſubtil than the Webs of Spiders,
<q>
                     <l>Fidem minutis diffecant ambagibus</l>
                     <l>Ut quiſque eſt lingua nequior.</l>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Becauſe curious wits can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not content themſelves to touch hot coals with tongs, but they muſt take them up with their naked fingers, nor to apprehend myſteries of Religion by faith, without deſcanting upon them, and determining them by reaſon, whilſt themſelves confeſs that they are incomprehenſible by humane reaſon, and imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptible
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:170067:23"/>
by mans imagination; <hi>How Chriſt is preſent in the Sacrament can neither be perceived by ſenſe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Aq. p.</hi> 3. 1. 76. <hi>Art.</hi> 7.</note> 
                  <hi>nor by i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magination.</hi> The more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>excuſable is their preſumpti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to anatomiſe myſteries, and to determine ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naturall not revealed truths, upon their own heads, which if they were revealed were not poſſible to be compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended by mortall man; As vain an attempt, as if a Child ſhould think to lade out all the water of the Sea with a Cockleſhell.<note place="margin">Deut. 29.29.</note> 
                  <hi>Secret things belong to the Lord our God, but things revealed unto us, and our Children for ever.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This is the reaſon why we reſt in the words of Chriſt, <hi>This is my Body,</hi> leaving the
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:170067:23"/>
manner to him that made the Sacrament; we know it is Sacramentall and therefore efficacious, becauſe God was never wanting to his own Ordinances, where man did not ſet a bar againſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf. But to determine whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be corporeally or ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually, (I mean not only after the manner of a ſpirit, but in a ſpirituall ſenſe,) whether it be in the Soul only, or in the Hoſt alſo; And if in the Hoſt, whether by Conſubſtantiation or Tranſubſtantiation, whether by Production or Adduction, or Conſervation or Aſſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or by whatſoever other way bold and blind man dare conjecture, we deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine not.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:170067:24"/>
                  <note place="margin">Durand.</note>
                  <hi>Motum ſentimus, modum neſcimus, praeſentiam credimus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This was the belief of the Primitive Church, this was the Faith of the antient Fathers, who were never ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with theſe modern queſtions <hi>de modo,</hi> which e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>difie not, but expoſe Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Religion to contempt. We know what to think, and what to ſay with pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bability, modeſty, and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion in the Schools; But we dare neither ſcrue up the Queſtion to ſuch an height, nor dictate our Opinions to others ſo Magiſterially as Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles of Faith.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Neſcire velle quae Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter maximus</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Docere non vult, erudita eſt inſcitia.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:170067:24"/>O!<note place="margin">Againſt multiply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of queſtions, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſies.</note> how happy had the Chriſtian world been, if Scholars could have ſate down contented with a la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of Generall, ſufficient, ſaving Truth, (which when all is done muſt be the Olive branch of peace, to ſhew that the deluge of Eccleſiaſticall diviſion is abated,) without wading too far into particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar ſubtilties, or <hi>doting about Queſtions and Logomac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ies, whereof commeth envy, ſtrife, raylings, evill ſurmiſings, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe diſputings.</hi> Old contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſies evermore raiſe up new controverſies, and yet more controverſies, as Circles in the water do produce other Circles.</p>
               <p>Now eſpecially theſe Scho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſticall quarrels ſeem to be
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:170067:25"/>
unſeaſonable, when <hi>Zenos</hi> School is newly opened in the world, who ſometimes wanted opinions, but never wanted Arguments; Now when Atheiſm and ſacrilege are become the mode of the times; Now when all the fundamentals of Theology, Morality, and Policy, are undermined and ready to be blown up; Now when the unhappy contentions of great Princes, or their Miniſters, have hazarded the very be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Monarchy and Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity; Now when <hi>Bello<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia</hi> ſhakes her bloody whip over this Kingdom, it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cometh well all good Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, and ſubjects, to leave their litigious queſtions, and <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note>to bring water to quench the
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:170067:25"/>
fire of civil diſſention alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy kindled, rather than to blow the Coals of diſcord, and to render themſelves cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurable by all diſcreet per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, like that half-wirted fellow perſonated in the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rator, <hi>Qui cum Capit is mede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri debuiſſet reduviem cura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vit;</hi> when his head was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremely diſtempered, he bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſied himſelf about a ſmall puſh on his fingers end.</p>
               <p>But that which createth this trouble to you and me at this time, is your Preface,<note place="margin">The Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of this Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe.</note> and Epiſtle Dedicatory; wherein to adorn your vain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly imagined Victory in an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſonable Controverſie, you reſt not contented, that your Adverſary grace your Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph, unleſs the King of
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:170067:26"/>
great <hi>Britain,</hi> and all his ſubjects, yea and all Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants beſides attend your Chariot. Neither do you on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly deſire this, but augurate it, or rather you relate it as a thing already as good as don:<note place="margin">P. 37.</note> for you tell him, that <hi>his eyes and his ears do hear and ſee thoſe truths, which make him to know the faults of that new Religion which he had ſucked in with his milk;</hi> you ſet forth the cauſes of his Converſion, <hi>The tears of his Mother, and the Blood of his Father,</hi> whom you ſuppoſe (againſt evident truth) to have dyed an inviſible Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of your Roman Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Church. And you pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe the means to perfect his Converſion, which muſt
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:170067:26"/>
be <hi>a conference of your Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logians with the Miniſters of Charentou.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If your charity be not to be blamed,<note place="margin">The Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſcretion.</note> to wiſh no worſe to another than you do to your ſelf, yet prudent men de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire more diſcretion in you, than to have preſented ſuch a Treatiſe to the view of the world under his Majeſties protection, without his licence and againſt his conſcience: Had you not heard that ſuch groundleſs inſinuations as theſe and other private whiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perings concerning his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Apoſtatiſing to the Roman Religion did loſe him the hearts of many ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects? If you did, why would you inſiſt in the ſame ſteps, to deprive the Son of
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:170067:27"/>
all poſſibility of recovering them?</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">To no purpoſe.</note>If your intentions be only to invite his Majeſty to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace the Catholick Faith,<note place="margin">The King is already a better Catholick than him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf.</note> you might have ſpared both your Oyl and labour. The Catholick Faith flouriſhed 1200. years in the world, before Tranſubſtantiation was defined among your ſelves. Perſons better acquainted with the Primitive times than your ſelf (unleſs you wrong one another) do acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge <hi>that the Fathers did not touch either the word or the matter of tranſubſtantia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Diſcurſus modeſtus Jeſuitaru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> p. <hi>13. Wat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons</hi> quod- lib. l. <hi>2.</hi> Art. <hi>4.</hi>
                  </note> Mark it well, neither name nor thing. His Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty doth firmly beleeve all ſupernaturall truths revea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led in ſacred Writ. He em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braceth
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:170067:27"/>
cheerfully whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever the holy Apoſtles, or the <hi>Nicene</hi> Fathers, or bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> in their reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pective Creeds or Summaries of Catholick Faith did ſet down as neceſſary to be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved. He is ready to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive whatſoever the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Church of this age doth unanimouſly believe to be a particle of ſaving Truth.</p>
               <p>But if you ſeek to obtrude upon him the Roman Church, with its adherents, for the Catholick Church, excluding three parts of four of the Chriſtian world from the Communion of Chriſt, or the opinions thereof for Articles and fundamentals of Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Faith, neither his rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, nor his Religion, nor his
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:170067:28"/>
charity will ſuffer him to li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten unto you. The Truths received by our Church are ſufficient in point of Faith to make him a good Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick. More than this your Roman Biſhops, your Roman Church, your <hi>Tridentine</hi> Councill, may not, cannot obtrude upon him. Liſten to the third generall Councill,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Par.</hi> 2. <hi>Act.</hi> 6. <hi>c.</hi> 7.</note> that of <hi>Epheſus,</hi> which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed, that <hi>it ſhould be lawfull for no man to publiſh or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe another Faith or Creed than that which was defined by the</hi> Nicene <hi>Councill,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Not law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to add to the old Creed.</note> 
                  <hi>And that whoſoever ſhould dare to compoſe or offer any ſuch to any perſons willing to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted from Paganiſm, Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daiſm, or Hereſy, if they were Biſhops or Clerks ſhould be
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:170067:28"/>
depoſed, if Laymen anathema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Suffer us to enjoy the ſame Creed the Primitive Fathers did, <hi>which none will ſay to have been inſufficient except they be mad,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Concil. Flor. Seſs. <hi>10.</hi> prof. ſid. in bulla Pti quarti.</note> as was alleged by the Greeks in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cill of <hi>Florence.</hi> You have violated this Canon, you have obtruded a new Creed upon <hi>Chriſtendom.</hi> New I ſay, not in words only; but in ſenſe alſo.</p>
               <p>Somethings are <hi>de Symbolo,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">What are additions to the Creed, and what are only ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plications.</note> ſomethings are <hi>contra ſymbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum,</hi> and ſomethings are only <hi>praeter ſymbolum.</hi> Somethings are conteined in the Creed, either expreſly or virtually, either in the Letter or in the ſenſe, and may be deduced by evident conſequence from
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:170067:29"/>
the Creed, as the Deity of Chriſt, his two natures, the proceſſion of the Holy Ghoſt. The addition of theſe was properly no addition, but an explication. Yet ſuch an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication, no perſon, no Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly under an Oecumeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Councill,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Aq.</hi> 2. 2. <hi>q.</hi> 1. <hi>Art.</hi> 10.</note> can impoſe upon the Catholick Church. And ſuch an one your <hi>Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentine</hi> Synod was not.</p>
               <p>Secondly, ſomethings are <hi>contra ſymbolum,</hi> contrary to the ſymbolicall Faith, and either expreſly or virtually overthrow ſome Article of it. Theſe additions are not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly unlawfull, but hereticall alſo in themſelves, and after conviction render a man a for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal Heretick; whether ſome of your additions be not of this
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:170067:29"/>
nature, I will not now diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, ſomethings are nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the Faith, nor againſt the Faith, but only beſides the Faith; That is, opinions or truths of an inferior na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, which are not ſo ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to be actually known: for though all revealed truths be a like neceſſary to be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved when they are known, yet all revealed truths are not a like neceſſary to be known. It is not denyed, but that Generall or Provinciall Councils may make con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions concerning theſe for unity and uniformity, and oblige all ſuch as are ſubject to their juriſdiction to receive them, either active<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, or paſſively, without con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tumacy
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:170067:30"/>
or oppoſition. But to make theſe, or any of theſe, a part of the Creed, and to oblige all Chriſtians un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der pain of damnation to know and believe them, is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally to adde to the Creed, and to change the Symbolicall, Apoſtolicall Faith, to which none can adde, from which none can take away, and comes within the compaſs of St. <hi>Pauls</hi> curſe,<note place="margin">Gal. 1.8.</note> 
                  <hi>If we, or an Angell from Heaven, ſhall Preach unto you any other Goſpell</hi> (or Faith,) <hi>than that which we have Preached, let him be accurſed.</hi> Such are your Univerſality of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Church, by the Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of Chriſt, to make her the Mother of her Grand-Mother the Church of <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem,</hi>
                  <pb n="57" facs="tcp:170067:30"/>
and the miſtreſs of her many elder Siſters. Your Doctrine of Purgatory and Indulgences, and the Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of Images, and all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther novelties defined in the Councill of <hi>Trent,</hi> all which are comprehended in your New Roman Creed, and obtruded by you upon all the world to be believed un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der pain of damnation. He that can extract all theſe out of the old Apoſtolick Creed, muſt needs be an excellent Chymiſt, and may ſafely un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dercake to draw water out of a Pumice.</p>
               <p>That afflictions come not by chance,<note place="margin">P. 4. Croſſes are not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments but ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections, or tryals.</note> that proſperity is no evidence of Gods favour, or adverſity of his hatred; that croſſes impoſed by God
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:170067:31"/>
upon his ſervants, look more forwards towards their a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendment, than backwards to their demerits, and proceed not from a Judge revenging, but from a Father correcting, or (which you have omitted,) from a Lord Paramount pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving and magnifying before the world his own graces in his Servants for his glory and their Advantage, are unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niable Truths which we rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily admit. As likewiſe that the dim eye of man cannot penetrate into the ſecret diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſations of Gods tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall judgements and mercies in this life, ſo as to ſay this man is puniſhed, that other chaſtiſed, this third is only proved.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="59" facs="tcp:170067:31"/>But you forget all this ſoon after,<note place="margin">Which the Author preſently forgets.</note> when you take upon you to ſearch into, yea more, to determine the grounds and reaſons why <hi>the hand of God;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>P.</hi> 8.</note> 
                  <hi>aſwell as the Parliament, hath been ſo heavy upon the Head of his late Majeſty, and his royall Son.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">P. 14.</note> Namely on Gods part, <hi>becauſe he called himſelf the head of the Church. God purpoſing by his puniſhment, to teach all other Princes that are in the Schiſm, with what ſeverity he can vindicate his glory in the injury done unto the Unity and Authority of his Church,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>P.</hi> 9.</note> And on the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments part, <hi>becauſe he would not conſent to the Abolition of Epiſcopacy, and ſuppreſſion of the Liturgy, and Ceremonies eſtabliſhed in the Church of</hi> England.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="60" facs="tcp:170067:32"/>Firſt, what warrant have you to enquire into the Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of that bleſſed Saint and Martyr, which of them ſhould be the cauſes of his ſufferings? Not remembring that the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples received a check from their Maſter upon the like preſumption;<note place="margin">Joh. 9.2.</note> 
                  <hi>Who ſinned? this man, or his parents, that he was born blind? Jeſus anſwered, neither hath this man ſinned, nor his parents, but that the works of God ſhould be made manifeſt in him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Better grounds of his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings, than thoſe of the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor.</note>The Heroicall Virtues, the flaming Charity, the admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Patience, the rare Humili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, the exemplary Chaſtity, the conſtant and frequent Devotions, and the invinci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Courage of that happy
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:170067:32"/>
Prince, not daunted with the ugly face of a moſt horrid death, have rendred him the glory of his Country, the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of that Church whereof he was the chiefeſt member, the admiration of Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and a pattern for all Princes, of what Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſoever, to imitate untill the end of the world. His Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frings were Palms, his Priſon a Paradiſe, and his death-day the birth-day of his happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; whom his Enemies ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantaged more by their cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty, than they could have done by their courteſie. They deprived him of a corruptible Crown, and inveſted him with a Crown of glory; They ſnatched him from the ſweet ſociety of his deareſt Spouſe,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:170067:33"/>
and from moſt hopefull <hi>Olive branches,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pſa. 128.3</note> to place him in the boſoms of the holy Angels. This alone is ground enough for his ſuffrings, to manifeſt unto the world thoſe tranſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent and unparallel'd graces, wherewith God had enriched him, to which his ſuffrings gave the greateſt luſtre, as the ſtars ſhine brighteſt in a dark night.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors raſh cenſure upon the Archbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Cant.</hi>
                  </note>The like liberty you aſſume towards the other moſt glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Martyr, the late Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> a man of profound learning, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emplary life, of clean hands, of a moſt ſincere heart, a pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tron of all good learning, a Profeſſor of antient truth, a great friend indeed, and ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt purſuer, of Order, U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:170067:33"/>
and uniformity in Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, but moſt free from all ſiniſter ends, either a varitious or ambitious, wherewith you do uncharitably charge him, as if <hi>he ſought onely his own Grandeur,</hi> to make himſelf the head of a Schiſmaticall body. In brief, you therefore cenſure him, becauſe you did not know him. I wiſh all your great Eccleſiaſtiques had his Innocency, and fervent zeal for Gods Church, and the peace thereof, to plead for them at the day of Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               <p>By applying theſe particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Afflictions according to your own ungrounded Fancy, what a wide gap have you opened to the liberty and boldneſs of other men? who
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:170067:34"/>
if they ſhould aſſume to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves the ſame freedom that you have done, might ſay as much, with as much reaſon, concerning the preſſures of other great Princes abroad, that God afflicts them, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they will not become Proteſtants, as you can ſay that God afflicted our late King, becauſe he would not turn Papiſt.</p>
               <p>But if you will not allow his Majeſties ſuffrings to be meerly probatory; And if (for your ſatisfaction) there muſt be a weight of ſin found out to move the wheel of Gods juſtice, why do you not rather fix upon the body of his Subjects or at leaſt a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loyall part of them? Wee confeſs that the beſt of us did
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:170067:34"/>
not deſerve ſuch a Jewell,<note place="margin">Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigns may be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away for the ſins of their ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects.</note> that God might juſtly ſnatch him from us in his wrath for our ingratitude. Reaſon, Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and experience do all teach us, that it is uſuall with Almighty God, to look upon a body politique, or Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtique, as one man, and to deprive a perverſe people of a good and gracious Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, as an expert Phyſician by opening a vein in one member, cures the diſtempers of another.<note place="margin">Prov. 28.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>For the Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions of a Land, many are the Princes thereof.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It may be that two or three of our Princes at the moſt (the greater part whereof were Roman Catholiques,<note place="margin">Not above two or three of our Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Heads of the Church.</note>) did ſtile themſelves, or give others leave to ſtile them, <hi>the
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:170067:35"/>
Heads of the Church,</hi> within their Dominions. But no man can be ſo ſimple, as to conceive that they intended a ſpirituall headſhip to infuſe the life and motion of grace into the hearts of the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, ſuch an head is Chriſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone; No not yet an Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſticall headſhip; We did ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver believe that our Kings in their own perſons could exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe any act perteining either to the power of Order or Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction:<note place="margin">That is onely poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall heads. 1 Sam. 15.17.</note> Nothing can give that to another, which it hath not it ſelf. They meant one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a Civill or Politicall head, as <hi>Saul</hi> is called the Head of the Tribes of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> to ſee that publick peace be preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, to ſee that all Subjects, aſwell Eccleſiaſtiques as o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:170067:35"/>
do their duties, in their ſeverall places; to ſee that all things be managed for that great and Architectonicall end, that is the weal and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of the whole body poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tique, both for ſoul and body. If you will not truſt me, Hear our Church it ſelf, <hi>When we attribute the Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Government of the Church to the King,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Art. 37.</note> 
                  <hi>we do not give him any power to admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter the Word or Sacraments; but onely that Prerogative which God in holy Scripture hath alwayes allowed to Godly Princes, to ſee that all Sates and Orders of their Subiects, Eccleſiaſticall and Civill, do their duties, and to puniſh thoſe who are delinquent, with the civill Sword.</hi> Here is no
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:170067:36"/>
power aſcribed,<note place="margin">Expoſ. Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raphr. art. Conf. Ang. Art. <hi>37.</hi>
                  </note> no puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment inflicted, but meerly politicall, and this is appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved and juſtificed by <hi>S. Clara,</hi> both by reaſon, and by the example of the Parliament of <hi>Paris.</hi> Yet by vertue of this Politicall power, he is the Keeper of both Tables, the preſerver of true piety to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards God, as well as right Juſtice towards men; And is obliged to take care of the ſouls, aſwell as the skins and carkaſſes of his ſubjects.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours politicall heads.</note>This power, though not this name, the Chriſtian Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours of old aſſumed unto themſelves, to Convocate Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nods, to preſide in Synods, to confirm Synods, to eſtabliſh Eccleſiaſticall Laws, to receive appeals, to nominate Biſhops,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:170067:36"/>
to eject Biſhops, to ſuppreſs Hereſies, to compoſe Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall differences, in Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cils, out of Councils, by themſelves, by their delegates: All which is as clear in the Hiſtory of the Church, as if it were written with a beam of the Sun.</p>
               <p>This power,<note place="margin">The old Kings of <hi>England</hi> politicall heads.</note> though not this name, the Antient Kings of <hi>England</hi> ever exerciſed, not onely before the Reformation, but before the Norman Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt, as appears by the Acts of their great Councills, by their Statutes, and Articles of the Clergy, by ſo many Laws of proviſion againſt the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Romes</hi> conferring Eccleſiaſticall dignities and benefices upon foreiners, by ſo many ſharp oppoſitions a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:170067:37"/>
the exactions and uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pations of the Court of <hi>Rome,</hi> by ſo many Laws concerning the Patronage of Biſhopricks, and Inveſtitures of Biſhops, by ſo many examples of Church-men puniſhed by the Civill Magiſtrate. Of all which Jewels the Roman Court had undoubtedly rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed the Crown, if the Peers and Prelates of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom had not come in to the reſcue.</p>
               <p>By the antient Laws of <hi>England</hi> it is death, or at leaſt a forfeiture of all his goods, for any man to publiſh the Popes Bull without the Kings Licence. The Popes Legate without the Kings leave could not enter into the Realm. If an Ordinary did refuſe to accept
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:170067:37"/>
a reſignation,<note place="margin">See Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorities for all theſe in <hi>Cawdries</hi> Caſe, in Judge <hi>Crook</hi> his Reports.</note> the King might ſupply his defect. If any Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall Court did exceed the bounds of its juſt power, either in the nature of the cauie, or manner of proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, the Kings Prohibition had place. So in effect the Kings of <hi>England</hi> were al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies the Politicall heads of the Church within their own Dominions. So the Kings of <hi>France</hi> are at this day.</p>
               <p>But who told you that ever King <hi>Charles</hi> did call himſelf the Head of the Church?<note place="margin">Neither K. <hi>Charles,</hi> K. <hi>James,</hi> nor Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> ſtiled heads of the Church.</note> thereby to merit ſuch an hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy Judgement. He did not, nor yet King <hi>James</hi> his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, nor Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> before them both, who took Order in her firſt Parliament, to have it left out of her Title;
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:170067:38"/>
They thought that name did ſound ill, and that it intrench<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed too far upon the right of their Saviour. Therefore they declined it, and were called onely Supreme Governours, in all Cauſes, over all perſons Eccleſiaſticall and Civill; which is a Title <hi>de jure</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeparable from the Crown of all ſoveraign Princes; Where it is wanting <hi>de facto</hi> (if any place be ſo unhappy to want it,) the King, is but half a King, and the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth a Serpent with two Heads.</p>
               <p>Thus you ſee, you are doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and both wayes miſerably miſtaken. Firſt, King <hi>Charles</hi> did never ſtile himſelf Head of the Church, nor could with patience endure to hear that
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:170067:38"/>
Title. Secondly, a Politicall Headſhip is not <hi>injurious to the Unity, or Authority of the Church.</hi> The Kings of <hi>Iſrael</hi> and <hi>Judah;</hi> the Chriſtian Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours, the Engliſh Kings before the Reformation, yea, even before the Conqueſt, and other Soveraign Princes of the Roman Communion have owned it ſignally.</p>
               <p>But it ſeems you have been told, or have read, this in the virulent writings of <hi>Sanders,</hi> or <hi>Parſons,</hi> or have heard of a ludicrous ſcoffing propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of a Marriage between the two heads of the two Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, <hi>Sixtus Quintus,</hi> and Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uniting forſooth of Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome. All the ſatisfaction, I ſhould enjoyn you, is to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:170067:39"/>
the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> (if <hi>Gregory</hi> the <hi>Great</hi> were living,<note place="margin">The Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction to perſwade the Pope to leave that vain Title.</note> you could not fail of ſpeeding,) to imitate the piety and humility of our Princes; that is, to content himſelf with his Patriarchicall dignity and primacy of Order, <hi>&amp; Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pium unitatis,</hi> and to quit that much more preſumptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and (if a Popes word may paſs for current) Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian terme of the <hi>Head of the Catholick Church.</hi> If the Pope be the Head of the Catholique Church, then the Catholique Church is the Popes body, which would be but an harſh expreſſion to Chriſtian ears; then the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Church ſhould have no Head, when there is no Pope, two or three Heads,
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:170067:39"/>
when there are two or three Popes; an unſound Head, when there is an hereticall Pope; a broken Head, when the Pope is cenſured or depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed; and no Head, when the See is vacant. If the Church muſt have one Univerſall, vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, Eccleſiaſticall Head, a generall Councill may beſt pretend to that Title.</p>
               <p>Neither are you more ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsfull in your other Reaſon,<note place="margin">Hatred of Epiſcopa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy or the true cauſe why the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted the King.</note> why the Parliament perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the King; <hi>Becauſe he mainteined Epiſcopacy, both out of Conſcience and Intereſt, which they ſought to aboliſh.</hi> For though it be eaſily admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, that ſome ſeditious and heterodox perſons had an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill eye, both againſt Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy, and Epiſcopacy, from the
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:170067:40"/>
very beginning of theſe trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, either out of fiery zeal, or vain affectation of Novel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, (like thoſe, who having the green-ſickneſs, prefer chalk and meal in a corner, before wholſome meat at their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers table,) or out of a gree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and covetous deſire of ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering ſome ſticks for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves upon the fall of thoſe great Okes, yet certainly they: who were the contrivers, and principall actors in this buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, did more malign Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copacy for Monarchy's ſake, then Monarchie for Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacies. What end had the <hi>Nuncio</hi>'s faction in <hi>Ireland</hi> againſt Epiſcopacy? whoſe mutinous courſes apparantly loſt that Kingdom. When the Kings conſent to the Aboli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:170067:40"/>
of Epiſcopacy in <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> was extorted from him by the Presbyterian faction (which probably the prime authors do rue ſufficiently by this time) were thoſe Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terian Scots any thing more favourable to Monarchy? To come to <hi>England,</hi> the chief Scene of this bloody Tragedy: If that party in Parliament had at firſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed any ſuch thing, as the Abolition either of Monarchy, or Epiſcopacy, undoubtedly they had ruined their whole deſign; untill daily tumults, and uncontrollable uprores had chaſed away the greater, and ſounder part of both Houſes: Their firſt Proteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was ſolemnly made to God, both for King and
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:170067:41"/>
Church, as they were by Law eſtabliſhed.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The true cauſes of the trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles in <hi>Engl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>d.</hi>
                  </note>Would you know then what it was that Conjur'd up the ſtorm among us? It was ſome feigned jealouſies and fears, (which the firſt broachers themſelves knew well enough to be fables) diſperſed cunningly among the people, <hi>That the King pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to ſubvert the funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall Lawes of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and to reduce the free Engliſh Subject to a condition of abſolute ſlavery under an Arbitrary Government.</hi> For which maſſy weight of mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious untruth, they had no ſupporters, but a few Bull<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſhes. Secondly, that he meant to apoſtate from the Proteſtant Religion to Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:170067:41"/>
and to that end had raiſed the Iriſh Rebellion by ſecret encouragements, and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſions; For which mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous calumny, they had no other foundation (except the ſolemn religious Order of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Service in his own Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, and Cathedral Churches) then ſome unſeaſonable diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putes about an Altar, or a Table, and the permiſſion of the Popes Agent, to make a ſhort ſtay in <hi>England,</hi> more for reaſons of State than of Religion. And ſome ſenſleſs fictions of ſome Iriſh Rebels, who having a Patent under the great Seal of <hi>Ireland</hi> for their Lands, to colour their barbarous murthers, ſhewed it to the poor ſimple people as a Commiſſion from the
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:170067:42"/>
King to levy forces. And laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſome impious pious frauds of ſome of your own partie, whoſe private whiſpers, and printed inſinuations did give hopes, that the Church of <hi>England,</hi> was comming about to ſhake hands with the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man in the points controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; Which was meerly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſed to gull ſome ſilly crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, whom they found apt to be catched with chaff; for which they had no more pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>text of truth, than you have for your groundleſs intimations in this unwelcome dedication.</p>
               <p>Theſe ſuſpitions being com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded with Covetouſneſs, Ambition, Envy, Emulation, deſire of Revenge, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>content, were the ſourſe of all our Calamities. Thus much
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:170067:42"/>
you your ſelf confeſs in effect; that, <hi>this ſuppoſition, that the King and Biſhops had an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention to re-eſtabliſh the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Catholique Religion, was the venom which the Puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan faction infuſed into the hearts of the people,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>P.</hi> 11.</note> 
                  <hi>to fill them with hatred againſt a King worthy of love; And the Parliament judged it a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourable occaſion for their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign, to advance themſelves to Soveraign Authority,</hi> Be Judge your ſelf how much they are acceſſary to our ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings, who either were, or are the Authors, or fomenters of theſe damnable ſlanders.</p>
               <p>There was yet one cauſe more of this cruell perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which I cannot conceal from you, becauſe it concerns
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:170067:43"/>
ſome of your old acquaintance. There was a Biſhop in the world (loſers muſt have leave to talk) whoſe privie Purſe, and ſubtill Counſells, did help to kindle that unnatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall war in his Majeſties three Kingdomes. Our Cardinall <hi>Wolſey</hi> complained before his death, <hi>That he had ſerved his King better than his God.</hi> But certainly this practiſe in your friend, was neither Good ſervice to his God, to be the author of the effuſion of ſo much innocent blood, nor yet to his King, to let the world ſee ſuch a dangerous preſident. It is high time for a man to look to himſelf, when his next neighbours houſe is all on a flame.</p>
               <p>As hitherto I have follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:170067:43"/>
your ſteps, though not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together in your own Method, or rather your own confuſion; So I ſhall obſerve the ſame courſe for the future. Your diſcourſe is ſo full of <hi>Mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi> and windings, turnings, and returnings, you congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate Heterogenious matter, and ſegregate that which is <hi>homogeneous,</hi> as if you had made your Dedication by ſtarts, and ſnatches; and never digeſted your whole diſcourſe; On the contrary, where I meet with any thing, it ſhall be my deſire to diſpatch it out of my hands, with whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver perteins unto it once for all. I hope you expect not that I ſhould amuſe my ſelf at your Rhetoricall flowers, and elegant expreſſions; they
<pb facs="tcp:170067:44"/>
agree well enough with the work you were about; The Pipe playes ſweetly, whilſt the Fowler is catching his prey. Trappings are not to be condemned, if the things themſelves are good and uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, but I prefer one Pome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>granate Tree loaden with good fruit, before a whole row of Cypreſſes, that ſerve onely for ſhew. Be ſure of this, that where any thing in your E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle reflects upon the Church of <hi>England,</hi> I ſhall not miſs it firſt or laſt, though it be but a looſe unjoynted peece, and ſo perhaps hitherto un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touched.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">We are onely ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed of Schiſm.</note>Amongſt other things which you lay to our charge, you glance, at the leaſt twelve times, at our ſuppoſed Schiſm.
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:170067:44"/>
But from firſt to laſt, never attempt to prove it, as if you took it for granted. I have ſhaped a Coat for a Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick, and had preſented it to you in this anſwer, but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering that the matter is of moment, and merits as much to be ſeriouſly and ſolidly weighed, as your naked Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination without all pretext of proof deſerves to be ſleigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, leſt it might ſeem here as an impertinent digreſſion, to take up too much place in this ſhort diſcourſe, I have added it at the Concluſion of this Anſwer, in a ſhort Tract by it ſelf, that you may per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſe it if you pleaſe.<note place="margin">Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians and Browniſts have been <hi>Romes</hi> beſt friends.</note>
               </p>
               <p>You fall heavily, in this Diſcourſe, upon the Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians, Browniſts, and Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendents,
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:170067:45"/>
if they intend to return you any anſwer, they may ſend it by a meſſenger of their own. As for my part, I am not their Proctor, I have received no Fee from them. And if I ſhould under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take to plead their Cauſe up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on my own head, by our old Engliſh Law, you might call me to accompt for unlawfull maintenance. Onely give me leave as a by-ſtander to won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der why you are ſo cholerique againſt them, for certainly they have done you more ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice in <hi>England,</hi> then ever you could have done for your ſelves.</p>
               <p>And I wonder no leſs why you call our Reformation, <hi>a Calviniſticall Reformation, brought into</hi> England <hi>by</hi> Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer,
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:170067:45"/>
                  <hi>and</hi> Peter Martyr, <hi>a blind Reformation, yea, the intire ruine of the Faith, of the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry form of the Church, and of the civill Government of the Common-wealth inſtituted by God.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>P.</hi> 16.</note> Though you confeſs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain in our favour, that <hi>if our firſt Reformers had been in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrogated, whether they meant:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>P.</hi> 19.</note> 
                  <note place="margin">P. 14.</note> 
                  <hi>any ſuch thing, they would have purged themſelves,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>P.</hi> 17.</note> 
                  <hi>and avouched their Innocence with their hands upon the new Goſpell.</hi> The gifts of Enemies are no gifts. If ſuch as theſe are all your courteſies, you may be pleaſed to take them again; Our firſt Reformers might ſafely ſwear upon any Goſpell, old, or new, that they meant no ſuch thing. And we may as ſecurely ſwear upon
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:170067:46"/>
all the books of God, old or new, that there is no ſuch thing. But why our Goſpell ſhould be younger or newer than <hi>Sixtus Quintus</hi> his Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, or <hi>Clemens Octavus</hi> his Goſpell, paſſeth my under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, and yours alſo.</p>
               <p>Compariſons are odious, therefore I will not ſay, that the true Engliſh Proteſtant ſtanding to his own grounds, is the beſt ſubject in the world. But I do ſay, that he is as good a ſubject as any in the world, and our princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples as Innocent, and as auxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liary to civill Government, as the Maximes of any Church under Heaven. And more than yours, where the claſhing of two Supreme Authorities, and the exemption of your
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:170067:46"/>
numerous Clergy from the Coercive power of the Prince, and ſome other novelties which I forbear to mention, do alwayes threaten a ſtorm.</p>
               <p>Tell me Sir, if you can, what Church in Europe hath declared more fully, or more favourably for Monarchy than the poor Church of <hi>England,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">L. <hi>Cant.</hi> 1643. <hi>C.</hi> 1.</note> 
                  <hi>That the moſt high and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Order of Kings, is of Divine Right, being the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance of God himſelf, foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in the prime Lawes of Nature, and clearly establiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by expreſs Texts, both of the old, and new Teſtament.</hi> Moreover, that <hi>this power is extended over all their Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, Eccleſiaſticall and Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill; That to ſet up any Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendent coactive power above
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:170067:47"/>
them, either Papall, or popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar, either directly, or indirect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, is to undermine their great royall Office, and cunningly to overthrow that moſt Sacred Ordinance, which God himſelf hath eſtabliſhed.</hi> That <hi>for their ſubjects to bear Arms against them, Offenſive, or defenſive upon any pretence whatſoever, is to reſiſt the powers which are ordeined of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation not Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viniſt. cal.</note>And why do you call our Reformation Calviniſticall, contrary to your own Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, contrary to your own confeſſion, That <hi>in our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation we reteined the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient Order of Epiſcopacy,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>P.</hi> 9.</note> 
                  <hi>as Inſtituted by divine authority, and a Liturgy, and Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, whereby we preſerved the
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:170067:47"/>
face, or Image of the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Church.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">P. 10.</note> And that <hi>for this very cauſe the diſciplina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians of</hi> Geneva, <hi>and the Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterians did conceive an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>placable hatred againſt the King for the Churches ſake, and out of their averſion to it.</hi> Did they hate their own Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation ſo implacably? If theſe things be to be reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, <hi>reddat mihi minam Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genes.</hi> He that looks more in diſputation to the Advantage of his partie, than to the truth of his grounds, had need of a ſtrong memory; We reteined not onely <hi>Epiſcopacy, Liturgy,</hi> and <hi>Ceremonies,</hi> but all things elſe that were conformable to the diſcipline, and publick ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of the primitive Church rightly underſtood.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="92" facs="tcp:170067:48"/>No, Sir, we cannot pin our faith upon the ſleeve of any particular man, as one uſed to ſay <hi>We love no niſmes;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">M. Tho. Sq.</note> neither <hi>Calviniſm,</hi> nor <hi>Lutheraniſme,</hi> nor <hi>Jonſenianiſm,</hi> but onely one, that we derive from <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioch,</hi> that is <hi>Chriſtianiſm,</hi> We honour Learning, and Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety in our fellow ſervants, but we deſire to wear no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther badge or Cognizance, than that we received from our own Maſter at our Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm. <hi>Bucer</hi> was as fit to be <hi>Calvins</hi> Maſter, as his Scho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar. So long as <hi>Calvin</hi> conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued with him in <hi>Germany,</hi> he was for <hi>Epiſcopacy, Litur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy,</hi> and <hi>Ceremonies,</hi> (and for aſſurance thereof ſubſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed the <hi>Auguſtane Confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi>) and his late learned Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſor,
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:170067:48"/>
and aſſertor in <hi>Geneva, Monſieur Deodate,</hi> with ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry others of that Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on were not averſe from them. Or why do you call our Reformation blind? It was not blindneſs, but too much affectation of knowledge, and too much peeping into con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverted, and new fangled Queſtions that hath endama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged our Religion. It is you that teach the <hi>Colliers Creed,</hi> not we.</p>
               <p>Howſoever you pretend to prove that our Reformation was the ruine of the Church, and Common-wealth: wee expect you ſhould endeavour to prove it. You cannot ſo far miſtake your ſelf as to conceive your authority to be the ſame with us, that <hi>Py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thagoras</hi>
                  <pb n="94" facs="tcp:170067:49"/>
had among his Scho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars, to have his Dictates received for Oracles without proof; what did I ſay, that you pretend to prove it? That's too low an expreſſion, you promiſe us <hi>a demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of it,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>P.</hi> 19.</note> 
                  <hi>ſo lively and evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent that no reaſon ſhall be able to contradict it.</hi> Are you not afraid that too much ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation ſhould prejudice your diſcourſe by diminiſhing our applauſe?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quid tanto dignum feret hic promiſſor hiatu?</hi> Do you think of nothing now but Triumphs? <hi>Lively and evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent demonſtration, not to be contradicted by reaſon,</hi> is like the Phenix much talked of, but ſeldom ſeen. Moſt men, when they ſee a man ſtrip up
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:170067:49"/>
his ſleeves, and make too large promiſes of fair dealing, do ſuſpect jugling. No man pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clameth in the Market that he hath rotten wares to ſell; And therefore we muſt be carefull, notwithſtanding your great promiſes, to keep well <hi>Epicharmus</hi> his Jewell, <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member to diſtruſt.</hi> By your permiſſion, your gliſtering de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration is a very coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeit, not ſo valuable as a <hi>Briſtol</hi> Diamant, when it comes to be examined by the wheel.</p>
               <p>Sometimes nothing is more neceſſary than Reformation.<note place="margin">Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is ſometimes neceſſary.</note> Never was houſe ſo wel buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, that now and then nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded not reparation. Never Garden ſo well planted, but muſt ſometimes be weeded.
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:170067:50"/>
Never any order ſo well in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted, but in long tract of time there will be a ben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding and declining from its Primitive perfection, and a neceſſity of reducing it to its firſt principles. Are your Houſes of Religion which are Reformed, therefore the leſs Religious? Why then did all the Princes and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealths in <hi>Europe,</hi> Yea the Fathers themſelves in the Councill of <hi>Trent,</hi> cry out ſo often, ſo earneſtly, for a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation? yet were forced to content themſelves with a vain ſhadow for the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, as <hi>Ixion</hi> embraced a Cloud for <hi>Juno,</hi> or Children are often ſtilled with an emp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty bottle.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable to all per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially the Court of <hi>Rome.</hi>
                  </note>But Reformation is not
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:170067:50"/>
agreeable to all perſons. <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das</hi> loved not an Audit, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he kept the Bag. Dull Lethargick people had rather ſleep to death than be awa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked; to and mad phrenetick Bigots are apt to beat the Chirurgion that would bind up their wounds; but none are ſo averſe from Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion as the Court of <hi>Rome,</hi> where the very name is more formidable than <hi>Hannibal</hi> at the Gates, yea than all the five terrible things. No mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail they are afraid to have their Oranges ſqueeſed to their hands; if they were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible as they pretend there was no need of a Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, we wiſh they were, but we ſee they are not.</p>
               <p>On the other ſide,<note place="margin">There is danger in Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:170067:51"/>
be denyed that Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, when it is unſeaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable, or inordinate, or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſive, may do more hurt than good; when Reformers want juſt Authority, or due information, or have ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter ends, or where the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy may be of worſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence than the abuſe, or where men run out of one extreme into another; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is a rule in prudence, <hi>Not to remove an ill cuſtom, when it is well ſetled;</hi> Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs it bring great prejudices, and then it is better to give one account, why we have taken it away, than to be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies making excuſes why we do it not. Needleſs alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration doth diminiſh the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerable eſteem of Religion,
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:170067:51"/>
and leſſen the credit of an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient truths. Break Ice in one place, and it will crack in more. Crooked ſticks by bending ſtreight are ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times broken into two.</p>
               <p>There is a right mean be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween theſe extremes,<note place="margin">The right rule of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation.</note> if men could light on it, that is nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to deſtroy the body out of hatred to the ſores and Ulcers, nor yet to cheriſh the ſores and Ulcers, out of a doating affection to the body, that is, neither to deſtroy an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tient Inſtitutions, out of a zealous hatred to ſome new abuſers, nor yet to do at ſo upon antient Inſtitutions, as for their ſakes to cheriſh new abuſes.</p>
               <p>Our Reformation is juſt<note place="margin">Our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation not the ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in of Faith Church or Common-wealth.</note> as much the cauſe of the ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:170067:52"/>
of our Church and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth, as the building of <hi>Tenderden</hi> Steeple was the cauſe of <hi>Goodwins</hi> Sands, or the ruin of the Country thereabouts, becauſe they hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened both much about the ſame time.</p>
               <q>—Careat ſucceſſibus opto,</q>
               <p>May he ever want ſucceſs who judgeth of Actions by the Event. Our Reformation hath <hi>ruined the Faith,</hi> juſt as the plucking up of weeds in a Garden, ruins the good Herbs. It hath <hi>ruined the Church,</hi> juſt as a body full of ſuperfluous and vicious humours is ruined by an healthfull purgation. It hath <hi>ruined the Common-wealth,</hi> juſt as the pruning of the Vine ruins the Elm. No, no
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:170067:52"/>
Sir, Our ſufferings, for the Faith, for the Church, for the Monarchy, do proclame us Innocent to all the world, of the ruin either of <hi>Faith,</hi> or <hi>Church,</hi> or <hi>Monarchy.</hi> And in this capacity we chooſe ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to ſterve Innocents, than to ſwim in plenty as No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cents.</p>
               <p>But this is but one of your doubles to keep us from the right forme. It is your new <hi>Roman Creed</hi> that hath ruined the Faith. It is your Papall Court that hath ruined the Church. It is your new Doctrines of the Popes Omnipotence over tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall perſons in order unto ſpirituall ends, of abſolving ſubjects from their Oaths of Alleageance, of exempting
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:170067:53"/>
the Clergy from ſecular ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction, of the lawfulneſs of murthering Tyrants and excommunicated Princes, of aequivocation and the like, that firſt infected the world to the danger of Civill Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment. Yet far be it from me to make theſe the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Tenets of your Church, at any time, much leſs at this time, when they are much faln from their former cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit; neither can I deny that ſundry dangerous poſitions, deſtructive to all civill ſocie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, have been tranſplanted by our Sectaries, and taken too deep root in our quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, but never by our fault. If God ſhould grant us the benefit of an Oecumenicall or Occidentall Councill, it
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:170067:53"/>
would become both you and us in the firſt place to pluck up ſuch ſeditious opinions root and branch.</p>
               <p>You ſay our <hi>Calviniſtical Reformation</hi> (ſo you are plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to call it as you would have it, for the moderate and orderly Reformation of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> was the terror, and eye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſore of <hi>Rome</hi>) is founded <hi>up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on two maxims,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Our firſt ſuppoſed Maxim.</note> The on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hat <hi>the Church was faln to ruin and deſolation, and become guilty of Idolatry and Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Church cannot come to ruin or be be guilty of Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try or Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny.</note>
               </p>
               <p>This is neither our foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, nor our ſuperſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, neither our maxim, nor our Opinion. It is ſo far from it, that we hold and teach the direct contrary. Firſt, that the <hi>Gates of Hell
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:170067:54"/>
ſhall never prevail againſt the Univerſall Church, that though the rain deſcend, and the floods come, and the winds blow and beat upon it,</hi> yet it ſhall never fall <hi>to ruin or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation;</hi> becauſe <hi>it is builded upon a Rock.</hi> Secondly, we beleeve that the Catholick Church is the faithfull Spouſe of Chriſt, and cannot be guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Idolatry, which is ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall Adultery. Thirdly, we never ſaid, we never thought, that the Oecumenical Church of Chriſt was guilty of Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny. It is principled to ſuffer wrong, to do none, and by ſuffering to Conquer,<note place="margin">Chryſoſt.</note> as a flock of unarmed Sheep, in the midſt of a company of ravenous Wolves, <hi>A new and unheard of kind of warfare
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:170067:54"/>
as if one ſhould throw an hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full of dry flax, into the midſt of a flaming fire to extinguiſh it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But I preſume this is one of the Idiotiſms of your lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage,<note place="margin">Catholick and Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man not Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibles.</note> in which by the Church you alwaies under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand the Roman Church, making Roman and Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick to be convertibles. As if Chriſt could not have a Church, nor that Church any privileges, unleſs the Court of <hi>Rome</hi> might have the Monopoly of them. There is a vaſt difference, between the Catholick Church and a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarchall Church. The Ca-Catholick Church can never fail; any Patriarchall Church may Apoſtate and fail. We
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:170067:55"/>
have a promiſe that the Candle ſhall not be put out, we have no promiſe that <hi>the Candleſticks ſhall not be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rev. 2.5.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Church it ſelf not abſolutely faln to ruin.</note>But ſuppoſſing that (which wee can never grant) the Catholick Church and Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Church were Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibles, yet ſtill you do us wrong. Firſt we do not maintain, that the Roman Church it ſelf is faln <hi>to ruin and deſolation,</hi> we grant to it a true metaphy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicall being, though not a true morall being; we hope their errors are rather in ſuperſtructures, than in fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damentals; wee doe not ſay that the Plants of ſaving truth (which are common
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:170067:55"/>
to you and us) are plucked up by the roots in the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Church, but we ſay that they are over-grown with weeds, and in danger to be choked.</p>
               <p>Next for Idolatry,<note place="margin">Whether the Roman Church be guilty of Idolatry.</note> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and why, and how far, we accuſe your Church of it deſerves further Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Firſt you agree with us, That God alone is the Object of Religion, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently that all Religious worſhip is due terminative<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly only to him, that God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone is to be invocated, ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely or ultimately, that is ſo as to grant our requeſts and fulfill our deſires by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and that the Saints are not the <hi>objects of our pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers,</hi> but joynt petitioners
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:170067:56"/>
with us, and interceſſors for us to the throne of Grace.</p>
               <p>Secondly, we profeſs as well as you that there is a propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionable degree of honour, and reſpect, due to every crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture in Heaven and Earth, according to the dignity of it, and therefore more honour due to a glorified Spirit, than to a mortall man: But with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all we adde, that this honour is not <hi>ſervitutis</hi> but <hi>chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis,</hi> not of ſervice as to our Lords and Maſters, but of love and charity as to our friends and fellow ſervants, of the ſame kind and nature with that Honour which we give to holy men on Earth. And herein we are confident that we ſhall have your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="109" facs="tcp:170067:56"/>Thirdly, we agree in this alſo, that abundant love and duty doth extend an honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable reſpect from the perſon of a dear friend, or noble be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefactor, to his Poſterity, to his memory, to his Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to his Image, to his Reliques, to every thing that he loved, or that pertained to him, even to the Earth which he did tread upon, for his ſake. Put a <hi>Liefhebber,</hi> or <hi>Virtue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo,</hi> among a company of rare Pictures, and he will pick out the beſt pieces for their proper value: But a friend or a child will more eſteem the Picture of a Benefactor, or Anceſtor, for its relation. The reſpect of the one is terminated in the Picture, that of the other is radicated in the exemplar.
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:170067:57"/>
Yet ſtill an Image is but an Image, and the kinds of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect muſt not be confounded. The reſpect given to an I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage, muſt be reſpect proper for an Image, not Courtſhip, not Worſhip, not Adoration. More reſpect is due to the perſon of the meaneſt beggar, than to all the Images of Chriſt and his Apoſtles, and a 1000. Primitive Saints or Progenitors. Hitherto there is neither difference nor pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rill either of Idolatry; or ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition.</p>
               <p>Wherein then did conſiſt this guilt of Idolatry contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted by the Roman Church? I am willing for the preſent to paſs by the private abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of particular perſons, which ſeem to me no other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:170067:57"/>
chargeable upon the whole Church than for Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nivence. As the making I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages to counterfeit tears, and words, and geſtures, and complements, for advantage, to induce ſilly people to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that there was ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of divinity in them; and the multitude of fictiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Relicks and ſuppoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Saints, which credulity firſt introduced, &amp; ſince cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſs hath nouriſhed. I take no notice now of thoſe remote ſuſpitions or ſuppoſitions of the poſſibility of want of inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, either in the Prieſt that conſecrates the Sacrament, or in him that Baptiſed, or in the Biſhop that ordeined him; or in any one through the whole line of ſucceſſion;
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:170067:58"/>
in all which caſes (according to your own principles,) you give divine worſhip to cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poreall Elements, which is at leaſt materiall Idolatry.</p>
               <p>I will not ſtand now to examine the truth of your diſtinctions, of <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, yet you know well e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, that <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> is no reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious worſhip, and <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> is coin lately minted, that will not paſs for current in the Catholick Church. Whilſt your common people under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand not theſe diſtinctions of degrees of honour, what holds them from falling down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right into Idolatry?</p>
               <p>Neither do I urge how you have diſtributed the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tronage of particular Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, the Cure of ſeverall
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:170067:58"/>
Diſeaſes, the protection of all diſtinct profeſſions of men, and all kinds of crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, among the Saints, juſt as the Heathen did among their Tutelary Gods; nor how little warrant you have for this practiſe from experience; nor laſtly how you build more Churches, erect more Altars, offer more preſents, powr out more prayers, make more vows, perform more offices to the Mother than to the Son. Yet though we ſhould hold our peace, me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinks you ſhould ponder theſe things ſeriouſly, and either for your own ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, or ours, take away ſuch unneceſſary occaſions of ſcandall and diſunion.</p>
               <p>But I cannot omit, that
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:170067:59"/>
the Councill of <hi>Trent</hi> is not contented to enjoyn the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doration of Chriſt in the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, (which we never deny,) but of the Sacrament it ſelf, (that is, according to the common current of your Schoolmen, the Accidents or Species of Bread and Wine, becauſe it conteins Chriſt.) Why do they not adde upon the ſame grounds, that the pix is to be adored with di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine worſhip, becauſe it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teins the Sacrament? Divine honour is not due to the very Humanity of Chriſt, as it is abſtracted from the Deity, but to the whole perſon, Deity, and Humanity, hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtatically united. Neither the Grace of Union, nor the Grace of Unction can con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:170067:59"/>
more upon the Humanity, than the Humanity is capable of. There is no ſuch Union between the Deity and the Sacrament, neither immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atly, nor yet mediately, <hi>mediante corpore.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Neither do you ordinarily aſcribe <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> or divine wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip to a Crucifix, or to the Image of Chriſt, indeed not Terminatively but tranſeunt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ſo as not to reſt in the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage or Crucifix, but to paſs to the exemplar or perſon crucified. But why a piece of Wood ſhould be made partaker of divine honours even in <hi>Tranſitu,</hi> or in the paſſage, paſſeth my under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding. The Heathens wanted not the ſame pretext for all their groſs Idolatry.
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:170067:60"/>
Let them plead for themſelves <hi>Non ego,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>I do not wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip that ſtone which I ſee, but I ſerve him whom I do not ſee.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>Laſtly, whilſt you are plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to uſe them, I may not forget thoſe ſtrange inſolent forms of prayer, conteined in your books, even ultimate prayers, if we take the words as they ſound, directed to the Creatures, that they would, <hi>protect you at the hour of death,</hi> and <hi>deliver you from the devill,</hi> and <hi>confer ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall graces upon you,</hi> and <hi>admit you into Heaven,</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cibus meritiſque, <hi>by their pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers and merias.</hi> (You know what merit ſignifies in your language, a <hi>Condignity</hi> or at leaſt a <hi>Congruity</hi> of defer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.)
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:170067:60"/>
The expoſition of your Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors is, that they ſhould do all this for you by their pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, as improper a form of ſpeech, as if a ſuppliant in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending only to move an ordinary Courtier to mediate for him unto the King, ſhould fall down upon his Knees before the Courtier, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech him to make him an Earl, or a Knight, or to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow ſuch an Office or ſuch a Pardon upon him, or to do ſome other Grace for him, properly belonging to the Prerogative Royall. How a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees this with the words, <hi>Precibus meritiſque?</hi> A beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger doth not deſerve an Alms by asking it. This is a ſnare to ignorant perſons, who take the words to ſignifie as they
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:170067:61"/>
ſound. And (it is to be fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red,) doe commit down-right Idolatry by their Paſtors faults, who preſcribe ſuch im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proper forms unto them.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Court moſt Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannicall.</note>Concerning <hi>Tyranny</hi> which makes up the arriere of the firſt ſuppoſed <hi>Maxim:</hi> Wee do not accuſe the Roman Church of Tyranny, but the Roman Court. If either the unjuſt uſurpation of Sovereign power, or the extending there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of to the deſtruction of the Laws and Canons of the Church, yea, even to give a <hi>Non obſtante,</hi> either to the Inſtitution of Chriſt, or at leaſt to the uniform practiſe of the Primitive Ages, or to them both; If the ſwallowing up of all Eccleſiaſticall Juriſdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and the arrogating of a
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:170067:61"/>
ſupercivill power paramont; If the cauſing of poor people to trot to <hi>Rome,</hi> from all the Quarters of <hi>Europe,</hi> to waſt their livelihoods there; If the trampling upon Emperours, and the diſciplining of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchs be Tyrannicall, either the Court of <hi>Rome</hi> hath been Tyrannicall, or there never was Tyranny in the world.</p>
               <p>I doubt not but ſome great perſons, when they have had bloody Tragedies to act for their own particular ends, have ſometimes made the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Church a ſtalking horſe, and the pretence of Catholick Religion a blind, to keep their Policies undiſcerned: But if we conſider ſeriouſly, what cruelties have been really a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted throughout Europe, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:170067:62"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="119" facs="tcp:170067:62"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="120" facs="tcp:170067:63"/>
by the Inquiſitors Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, or by perſons ſpecially delegated for that purpoſe, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Waldenſes</hi> of old, and againſt the Proteſtants of later dayes, againſt poor igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant perſons, againſt women and children, againſt mad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, againſt dead carkaſſes, as <hi>Bucer,</hi> &amp;c. upon pretence of Religion, not onely by Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary forms of puniſhment, and of death, but by fire and faggots, by ſtrange new de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſed tortures, we ſhall quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly find that the Court of <hi>Rome</hi> hath died it ſelf red in Chriſtian blood, and equalled the moſt Tyrannicall perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the Heathen Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours.<note place="margin">Our ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed Maxim</note>
               </p>
               <p>The other Maxim where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon you ſay that our Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:170067:63"/>
was grounded was this; <hi>That the onely way to reform the Faith and Liturgy,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">P. 21.</note> 
                  <hi>and government of the Church, was to conform them to the dictates of holy Scripture, of the ſenſe whereof every private Chriſtian ought to be the Judge, by the light of the Spirit, excluding Tradition, and the publick Judgement of the Church.</hi> You add,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>P.</hi> 26.</note> that <hi>We cannot prove Epiſcopacy by Scripture without the Help of Tradition; And if we do ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit of Tradition, we must ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge the Papacy, for the Government of the Catholick Church, as founded in the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy of St.</hi> Peter.</p>
               <p>Your ſecond ſuppoſed ground is no truer than the former,<note place="margin">Much mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaken.</note> we are as far from
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:170067:64"/>
Anarchy as from Tyranny; As we would not have hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Authority, like <hi>Medu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa</hi>'s head, to transform reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable men into ſenſleſs ſtones; So we do not put the reigns of Goverment into the hands of each, or any private per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, to reform according to their phantaſies; And that we may not deal like blunderers, or deceitfull perſons, to wrap up on involve our ſelves on purpoſe in confuſed Generali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, I will ſet down our ſenſe diſtinctly; When you under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand it, I hope you will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent of your raſh cenſuring of us, of whom you had ſo little knowledge.<note place="margin">The Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture the rule of ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pernatural truths.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Three things offer them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to be conſidered: firſt, concerning the Rule of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture;
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:170067:64"/>
Secondly, the proper Expounders thereof, and third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the manner of Expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition.</p>
               <p>Concerning Scripture we believe, That it was impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble for humane reaſon, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the help of divine Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation, to find out thoſe ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pernaturall truths which are neceſſary to Salvation. 2. That to ſupply this defect of natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall reaſon, God out of his a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundant goodneſs hath given us the holy Scriptures, which have not their authority from the writing which is humane, but from the Revelation which is divine, from the holy Ghoſt. Thirdly, that this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the purpoſe of the Holy Ghoſt, it is blaſphemy to ſay he would not, or could not
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:170067:65"/>
attain unto it. And that therefore the holy Scriptures do comprehend all neceſſary ſupernaturall truths; So much is confeſſed by <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> that <hi>All things which are ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to be believed,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">L. <hi>4.</hi> de ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bo Dei, cap. <hi>11.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>and to be done by all Chriſtians, were preached to all by the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, and were all written.</hi> 4. That the Scripture is more properly to be called a Rule of ſupernaturall truths than a Judge, or if it be ſometimes called a Judge, it is no other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe than the Law is called a Judge of civill Controverſies between man and man, that is, the rule of judging what is right, and what is wrong. That which ſheweth what is ſtreight, ſheweth likewiſe what is crooked.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="125" facs="tcp:170067:65"/>Secondly,<note place="margin">Who are the proper expoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of Scripture, and ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> far.</note> concerning the proper Expounders of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, we do believe that the Goſpell doth not conſiſt in the words, but in the ſenſe, <hi>non in ſuperficie, ſed in medullâ;</hi> And therefore that though this infallible rule be given for the common benefit of all, yet every one is not an able or fit Artiſt to make ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of this Rule, in all particular caſes. To preſerve the common right, and yet prevent particular abuſes, we diſtinguiſh Judgement into three kinds.</p>
               <p>Judgement of Diſcretion, Judgement of Direction, and Judgement of Juriſdiction.</p>
               <p>As in the former Inſtance of the Law (the ignorance whereof excuſeth no man) e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:170067:66"/>
ſubject hath Judgement of Diſcretion, to apply it par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly to the preſervation of himſelf, his eſtate and inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt; The Advocates and thoſe who are skilfull in the Law, have moreover a Judgement of Direction, to adviſe others of leſs knowledge and expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience; But thoſe who are Conſtituted by the Soveraign power, to determine emergent difficulties, and differences, and to diſtribute, and admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter juſtice to the whole bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of a Province or King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, have moreover a Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Juriſdiction, which is not onely diſcretionary, or directive, but authoritative to impoſe an Obligation of obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience upon thoſe who are under their charge. If theſe
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:170067:66"/>
laſt ſhall tranſgreſs the rule of the Law, they are not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comptable to their Inferiours, but to him or them that have the Soveraign power of Legiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lative Judicature; <hi>Ejus eſt le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gem interpretari, cujus eſt condere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To apply this to the caſe in Queſtion concerning the expoſition of the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. Every Chriſtian keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himſelf within the bounds of due obedience and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to his lawfull Superi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours, hath a Judgement of <hi>Diſcretion, Prove all things,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Theſ. 5.21.</note> 
                  <hi>hold fast that which is good.</hi> He may apply the Rule of holy Scripture for his own private Inſtruction, comfort, edification, and direction, and for the framing of his life and
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:170067:67"/>
belief accordingly. The Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors of the Church, (who are placed over Gods people as watchmen and guides,) have more than this, a judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>Direction,</hi> to expound and interpret the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures to others, &amp; out of them to inſtruct the ignorant, to reduce them who wander out of the right way, to confute errors, to foretell dangers, and to draw ſinners to repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance. The chief Paſtors to whoſe care the Regiment of the Church is committed in a more ſpeciall manner, have yet an higher degree of judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, a Judgement of <hi>Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction</hi> to preſcribe, to enjoyn, to conſtitute, to reform, to cenſure, to condemn, to bind, to looſe, judicially, authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatively,
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:170067:67"/>
in their reſpective charges. If their Key ſhall erre, either their Key of Knowledge, or their Key of Juriſdiction, they are accomp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to their reſpective Supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riours, and in the laſt place to a generall Councill, which under Chriſt upon Earth, is the higheſt Judge of Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſies. Thus we have ſeen what is the Rule of Faith, and by whom, and how far reſpectively this rule is to be applied.</p>
               <p>Thirdly,<note place="margin">The man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounding Scripture.</note> for the manner of expounding holy Scriptures, (for there may be a privacy in this alſo, and more dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous than the privacy of the perſon,) many things are ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to the right interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of the Law, to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:170067:68"/>
the reaſon of it, the precedents, the terms, the forms, the Reports, and an ability to compare Law with Law. He that wants all theſe Qualifications altogether, is no interpreter of Law. He that wants but ſome of them, or wants the perfection of them, by how much the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is his defect, by ſo much the leſs valuable is his expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition; And if he ſhall out of private fancy, or blind pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption, arrogate to himſelf, without theſe requiſite means, or above his capacity and proportion of Knowledge, a power of expounding Law, he is a mad-man.</p>
               <p>So many things are requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to render a man capable to expound holy Scriptures,
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:170067:68"/>
ſome more neceſſarily, ſome leſs, ſome abſolutely, ſome re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectively; As firſt to know the right Analogy of Faith, to which all interpretations of Scripture muſt be of neceſſity conformed. Secondly, to know the practiſe and tradition of the Church, and the received expoſitions of former Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preters in the ſucceſſive ages, which gives a great light to the finding out of the right ſenſe. Thirdly, to be able to compare Texts with Texts. Antecedents with Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quents, without which one can hardly attain to the drift and ſcope of the holy Ghoſt in the obſcurer paſſages. And laſtly, it is ſomething to know the Idiotiſms of that language wherein the Scriptures were
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:170067:69"/>
written. He that wants all theſe requiſites, and yet takes upon him out of a phanatique preſumption of private illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination to interpret Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, is a doting Enthuſiaſt, fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to be refuted with Scorn than with Arguments. He that preſumes above that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree and proportion which he hath in theſe means, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove the talent which God hath given him, (as he that hath a little Language, yet wants Logick, or having both Language and Logick, knows not, or regards not either the Judgement of former expoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, or the practiſe, and tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of the pureſt primitive ages, or the Symbolicall faith of the Catholick Church) <hi>is not a likely work-man to build
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:170067:69"/>
a Temple to the Lord, but ruine and deſtruction to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and his ſeduced followers.</hi> A new Phyſician (we ſay) requires a new Church-yard; But ſuch bold ignorant Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricks in Theology, are ten times more dangerous to the Soul, than an ungrounded un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>experienced Quackſalver to the body.</p>
               <p>This hath alwayes been the doctrine,<note place="margin">This is conforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the doctrine and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe of our Church.</note> and the practice of our Engliſh Church; Firſt, it is ſo far from admitting laymen, to be directive In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreters of holy Scripture, that it allows not this Liberty to Clergy-men ſo much as <hi>to gloſs upon the Text,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Can.</hi> 1603. <hi>Can.</hi> 49.</note> untill they be Licenced to become Preachers. Secondly, for Judgement of Diſcretion on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:170067:70"/>
it gives it not to private perſons above their Talents,<note place="margin">See the Preface to the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</note> or <hi>beyond their laſt.</hi> It diſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows all phantaſticall, and Enthuſiaſticall preſumption of incompetent and unqualified expoſitors. It admits no man into holy Orders, that is, to be capable of being made a Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rective interpreter of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, howſoever otherwiſe qualified,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Cant.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>4.</note> unleſs he be able to give a good accompt of his faith in the Latin tongue, ſo as to be able to frame all his expoſitions according to the Analogy thereof.<note place="margin">Cant. <hi>1571.</hi> tit. Concio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natores.</note> It forbids the Licenced Preachers to <hi>teach the people any doctrine as neceſſary to be religiouſly held and believed, which the Catholique Fathers, and old Biſhops of the Primitive
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:170067:70"/>
Church, have not collected out of the Scriptures.</hi> It aſcribes a Judgement, of Juriſdiction over Preachers to Biſhops, in all manner of Eccleſiaſticall duties, as appears by the whole body of our Canons. And eſpecially where any dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference or publick Oppoſition hath been between Preachers,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Can.</hi> 1631. <hi>Can.</hi> 53.</note> about any point or doctrine deduced out of Scripture. It gives a power of determining all emergent Controverſies of faith above Biſhops to the Church,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Art.</hi> 20. <hi>Can.</hi> 1603. <hi>Can.</hi> 139.</note> as <hi>to the witneſs and keeper of the Sacred Oracles.</hi> And to a lawfull <hi>Synod as the repreſentative Church.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now, Sir, be your own Judge how infinitely you have wronged us, and your ſelf more, ſuggeſting that temera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly,
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:170067:71"/>
and without the Sphere of your knowledge, to his Majeſty for the principall ground of our Reformation, which our ſouls abhor. Is there no mean between ſtupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity and madneſs? Muſt ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther all things be lawfull for private perſons, or nothing? Becauſe we would not have them like <hi>Davids Horſe and Mule, without underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> do we therefore put both Swords in their hands, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form and cut off, to plant and to pluck up, to alter and aboliſh at their pleaſure? We allow them Chriſtian liberty, but would not have them Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertines. Admit ſome have abuſed this juſt liberty, may we therefore take it away from others? So we ſhall
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:170067:71"/>
leave neither a Sun in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, nor any excellent crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture upon Earth, for all have been abuſed by ſome per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, in ſome kinds, at ſome times.</p>
               <p>We receive not your up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtart ſuppoſititious traditions,<note place="margin">The Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Church an enemy to upſtart, not to A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtolicall traditions.</note> nor unwritten fundamentalls: But we admit, genuine, Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſall, Apoſtolicall traditions, As the Apoſtles Creed, the perpetuall Virginity of the Mother of God, the Anniver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary Feſtivals of the Church, the Lenton faſt. Yet we know that both the duration of it, and the maner of obſerving it, was very different in the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive times. We believe E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopacy to an ingenuous perſon may be proved out of Scripture without the help of
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:170067:72"/>
Tradition, but to ſuch as are froward, the perpetuall pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe and tradition of the Church renders the interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of the Text more au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thentique, and the proof more convincing. What is this to us who admit the practiſe and tradition of the Church, as an excellent help of Expoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? Uſe is the beſt interpreter of Laws, and we are ſo far from beleeving that <hi>We can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not admit tradition without allowing the Papacy,</hi> that one of the principall motives why we rejected the Papacy, as it is now eſtabliſhed with Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſality of Juriſdiction, by the Inſtitution of Chriſt, and ſuperiority above Oecumeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Councils, and Infallibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of Judgement, was the
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:170067:72"/>
conſtant tradition a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Church.</p>
               <p>So Sir, you ſee your de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration ſhaken into pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; You who take upon you to remove whole Churches at your pleaſure, have not ſo much ground left you as to ſee your Inſtrument upon. Your two main ground-works be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vaniſhed, all your Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterian and Independent ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtructions; do remain like ſo many Bubbles or Caſtles in the air. It were folly to lay cloſer ſiege to them, which the next puff of wind will diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſe, <hi>ruunt ſubductis tecta Columnis.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Howſoever, though you have miſtaken the grounds of our Reformation, and of your diſcourſe, yet you charge us,
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:170067:73"/>
that <hi>we have renounced the Sacrifice of the Maſs, Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantiation, the ſeven Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments, Juſtification by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haerent righteouſneſs, merits, Invocation of Saints, prayer for the dead, with Purgatory, and the Authority of the Pope.</hi> Are theſe all the neceſſary Articles of the new Roman Creed, that we have renoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced? Surely no; you deal too favourably with us. We have in like manner renounced your Image-worſhip, your half Communion, your pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers in a tongue unknown, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> It ſeems you were loath to mention theſe things.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Of the Sacrifice of the Maſs.</note>Firſt, you ſay we have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced your ſacrifice of the Maſs. If the Sacrifice of the Maſs be the ſame with the
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:170067:73"/>
Sacrifice of the Croſs, we at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute more unto it, than your ſelves; We place our whole hope of Salvation in it. If you underſtand another pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitiatory Sacrifice, diſtinct from that (as this of the Maſs ſeems to be, for confeſſedly the Prieſt is not the ſame, the Altar is not the ſame, the Temple is not the ſame,) If you think of any new meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious ſatisfaction to God for the ſins of the world, or of any new ſupplement to the merits of Chriſts Paſſion, You muſt give us leave to renounce your Sacrifice indeed, and to adhere to the Apoſtle;<note place="margin">Heb. 10.14</note> 
                  <hi>By one offering he hath perfected for ever them that are ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Surely you cannot think
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:170067:74"/>
that Chriſt did actually ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice himſelf at his laſt Supper, (for then he had redeemed the world at his laſt Supper, then his ſubſequent ſacrifice upon the Croſs had been ſuperflu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous,) nor that the Prieſt now doth more than Chriſt did then. We do readily acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge an Euchariſticall ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of prayers and praiſes, we profeſs a commemoration of the ſacrifice of the Croſs, And in the language of holy Church, things commemorated are rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted as if they were then acted, As <hi>Almighty God who haſt gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven us thy Son</hi> [as this day] <hi>to be born of a pure Virgin.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">In the Collects for theſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eaſts.</note> And <hi>whoſe praiſe the younger, Innocents have</hi> [this day] <hi>ſet forth.</hi> And between the Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſion and Pentecoſt, <hi>which
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:170067:74"/>
haſt exalted thy Son Jeſus Chriſt with great Triumph into Heaven, we beſeech thee leave us not comfortleſs, but ſend unto us thy holy Spirit.</hi> We acknowledge a Repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of that ſacrifice to God the Father, we acknowledge an Impetration of the benefit of it, we maintain an Appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of its vertue: So here is a commemorative, impetra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, applicative ſacrifice. Speak diſtinctly, and I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not underſtand what you can deſire more. To make it a ſuppletory ſacrifice, to ſupply the defects of the onely true ſacrifice of the Croſs, I hope both you and I abhor.</p>
               <p>The next crime objected by you to us is,<note place="margin">Of Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation.</note> that we have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced Tranſubſtantiation.
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:170067:75"/>
It is true we have rejected it deſervedly from being an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticle of our Creed; you need not wonder at that. But if we had rejected it 400. years ſooner, that had been a Mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle. It was not ſo ſoon hat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched. To find but the word Tranſubſtantiation in any old Author, were ſufficient to prove him a counterfeit.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Of 7. Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments.</note>Your next Article of the ſeptenary number of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments is not much older. Never ſo much as mentioned in any Scripture, or Councill, or Creed, or Father, or antient Author;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Anno</hi> 1439 1528. 1547.</note> firſt deviſed by <hi>Peter Lombard;</hi> firſt decreed by <hi>Eugenius</hi> the fourth; firſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed in the Provinciall Councill of <hi>Senes,</hi> and after in the Councill of <hi>Trent.</hi>
                  <pb n="145" facs="tcp:170067:75"/>
Either the word <hi>Sacrament</hi> is taken largely; and then the waſhing of the Diſciples feet is called a Sacrament, then the onely ſprink<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing of Aſhes on a Chriſtians head is called a Sacrament, then there are God knows how many Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments more than ſeven; Or elſe it is taken ſtrictly for a viſible ſign, inſtituted by Chriſt, to convey or confirm inviſible Grace, to all ſuch partakers thereof, as do not ſet a bar againſt themſelves, according to the Analogy be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Sign and the thing ſignified. And in this ſenſe the proper and certain Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the Chriſtian Church, common to all, or (in the words of our Church,) <hi>gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally neceſſary to Salvation,</hi>
                  <pb n="146" facs="tcp:170067:76"/>
are but two, Baptiſm and the Supper of our Lord. More than theſe <hi>St. Ambroſe</hi> writes not of in his Book <hi>de Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentis,</hi> becauſe he did not know them. Theſe we admit for genuine, and generall Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments. Their Sacramentall vertue we acknowledge.</p>
               <p>The reſt we retein more purely than your ſelves, though not under the Notion of ſuch, proper and generall Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. As Confirmation, Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination, Matrimony, Peni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence (though we neither ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove of your prepoſterous manner of Abſolution before ſatisfaction, nor of your Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary penitentiary tax,) and laſtly, the Viſitation of, and Prayer for the ſick, which onely is of perpetual neceſſity.
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:170067:76"/>
The Unction preſcribed by <hi>St. James,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Jam. 5.14.</note> being appropriable to the miraculous gift of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, or recovering men out of ſickneſſes, then in uſe; Whereas your cuſtome is clean contrary, never, or rare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to enoyl any man, untill he be paſt all hope of Reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very. The Ordinary and moſt received cuſtome of preparing ſick perſons for another world in the primitive Church, was Prayer and Abſolution, or the benefit of the Keys, and the <hi>Viaticum</hi> of the body and blood of Chriſt, which we retein.</p>
               <p>Concerning Juſtification,<note place="margin">Of Juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation.</note> we believe that all good Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans have true inherent Juſtice, though not perfect according to a perfection of degrees, as
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:170067:77"/>
gold is true Gold, though it be mixed with ſome droſs. We believe that this inherent Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice and ſanctity, doth make them truly juſt and holy. But if the word <hi>Juſtification</hi> be taken <hi>in ſenſu forenſi,</hi> for the acquittall of a man from for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer guilt, to make an offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der juſt in the eye of the Law, as it is oppoſed to Condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation,<note place="margin">Rom. 8.33</note> 
                  <hi>It is God that juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, who is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e that condemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth;</hi> Then it is not our inhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent righteouſneſs that juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies us in this ſenſe, but the free Grace of God for the merits of Jeſus Chriſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Of Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits.</note>Next for merits, we never doubted of the neceſſity of good Works, without which Faith is but a fiction. We are not ſo ſtupid to imagine
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:170067:77"/>
that Chriſt did waſh us from our ſins, that we might wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low more ſecurely in ſin, but that <hi>wee might ſerve him in holineſs and righteouſneſs all the dayes of our life.</hi> We ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver doubted of the reward of good Works; <hi>Come ye bleſſed of my Father,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>for I was hungry, and ye fed me.</hi> Nor whether this reward be due to them in Juſtice; <hi>Hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth is layd up for me a Crown of righteouſneſs,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Tim. 4.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>which the Lord the juſt Judge ſhall give me in that day.</hi> Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full promiſe makes due debt. This was all that the antient Church did ever underſtand by the name of Merits. Let <hi>Petavius</hi> bear witneſs;<note place="margin">Diſcrt. Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſ. li. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>4.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qui patres omnes &amp; prae cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teris Auguſtinus, cumque iis
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:170067:78"/>
conſentiens Romana &amp; Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lica pietas agnoſcit merita eò ſenſu, nimirum ut ne<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> Dei gratiam ulla antecedant meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta, &amp; haec ipſa tum ex gratiâ, tum ex gratuitâ Dei pollici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatione tota pendeant. All the Antient Fathers, eſpecially St.</hi> Auſtin, <hi>and the Roman and Catholique faith conſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with them, do acknowledge Merits in this ſenſe, that no Merits go before the grace of God, and that theſe very Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits do Depend wholly on grace, and on the free promiſe of God.</hi> Hold you to this, and we ſhall have no more diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence about Merits; Do you exact more of us, than all the Fathers, or the Roman and Catholique piety doth ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge?</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="155" facs="tcp:170067:78"/>It is an eaſie thing for a wrangling Sophiſter to diſpute of Merits, in the Schools, or for a vain Orator to declame of Merits out of the Pulpit, but when we come to ly up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on our death-beds, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent our ſelves at the laſt hour before the Tribunal of Chriſt, it is high time both for you and us to renounce our own merits, and to caſt our ſelves naked into the Arms of our Saviour. That any works of ours, who are the beſt of us but <hi>unprofitable ſervants,</hi> which properly are not ours but Gods own gifts, and if they were ours are <hi>a juſt debt</hi> due unto him, ſetting a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide Gods free promiſe, and gracious acceptation, ſhould condignly by their own in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trinſecall
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:170067:79"/>
value deſerve the joyes of Heaven, to which they have no more proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on than they have to ſatisfie for the eternall torments of Hell: This is that which we have renounced, and which we never ought to admit.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Of Invo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of Saints.</note>If your Invocation of Saints were not ſuch as it is, to requeſt of them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Patronage and Protection, ſpirituall gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and Celeſtiall joyes, by their prayers, and by their merits, (alas the niſeſt Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins have oyl in their Lamps little enough for themſelves;) Yet it is not neceſſary for two Reaſons; Firſt, no Saint doth love us ſo well as Chriſt. No Saint hath given us ſuch aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance of his love, or done ſo much for us as Chriſt. No
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:170067:79"/>
Saint is ſo willing, or able to help us as Chriſt. And ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, we have no command from God to invocate them.</p>
               <p>So much your own Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors do confeſs, and give this reaſon for it,<note place="margin">S. Clara Probl. <hi>37.</hi> ex Horan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio.</note> 
                  <hi>Leſt the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles being converted, ſhould believe that they vere drawn back again to the worſhip of the creature.</hi> But we have a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother command, <hi>Call upon me in the day of trouble, and I will hear thee.</hi> We have no promiſe to be heard, when we do invocate them; But we have another promiſe, <hi>What<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever ye ſhall ask the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in my Name, ye ſhall receive it.</hi> We have no ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample in holy Scripture of any that did invocate them, but rather the contrary; <hi>See
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:170067:80"/>
thou do it not;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rev. 22.9.</note> 
                  <hi>I am thy fellow ſervant, worſhip God.</hi> We have no certainty that they do hear our particular prayers, eſpecially mentall prayers, yea a thouſand pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers poured out at one Inſtant in ſeverall parts of the world; We know what your men ſay of the glaſs of the Trini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and of extraordinary Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velations: But theſe are bold conjectures without any cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty, and inconſiſtent the one with the other.</p>
               <p>We do ſometimes meet in antient Authors, with the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terceſſion of the Saints in Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall, which we alſo ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge; or an oblique in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocation of them (as you term it,) that is a prayer directed to God, that he will
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:170067:80"/>
hear the interceſſion of the Saints for us, which we do not condemn; Or a wiſh, or a Rhetoricall Apoſtrophe, or perhaps ſomething more in ſome ſingle antient Author: But for an Ordinary Invo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation in particular neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and much more for pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Invocation in the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgies of the Church, we meet not with it for the firſt ſix hundred years, or there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abouts; All which time and afterwards alſo, the common principles and tradition of the Church were againſt it. So far were they from obtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding it as a neceſſary funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall Article of Chriſtian Religion.<note place="margin">Of prayer for the dead with Purgatory.</note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>It is a common fault of your writers alwaies to cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:170067:81"/>
Prayer for the dead and Purgatory together, as if the one did neceſſarily ſuppoſe, or imply the other; In whoſe ſteps you tread. Prayer for the dead hath often procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded upon miſtaken grounds, often from true grounds, both inconſiſtent with your Purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory. Many have held an Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, that though the ſouls were not extinguiſhed at the time of their ſeparation from the body, yet they did lye in <hi>ſecret receptacles,</hi> in a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found or dead ſleep, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till the reſurrection, doing nothing, ſuffering nothing in the mean time, but only the delay of their glory. Others held that all muſt paſs through the fire of Conflagration at the day of judgement. Theſe
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:170067:81"/>
opinions were inconſiſtent with your Purgatory, yet all theſe, upon theſe very grounds uſed prayer for the dead. Others called the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull Doctors, held, that the very pains of Hell might be leſſened by the prayer of the living: Such a prayer is that which we meet with in your own Miſſall, <hi>O King of Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, deliver the ſouls of all the faithfull deceaſed, from the pains of Hell, from the deep lake,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Tartarus.</note> 
                  <hi>from the mouth of the Lion</hi> (that is the Devill,) <hi>that the bottomleſs pit of Hell do not ſwallow them up.</hi> A man may lawfully pray for that which is certain, if it be to come, but one cannot lawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly pray for that which is paſt. The ſouls which are in Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:170067:82"/>
(by your learning,) are paſt the fear of Hell. Nor can this petition be any ways ſo wreſted, as to become ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliable to the hour of death. This prayer is not for the man, but for the ſoul ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated; nor for the ſoul of a ſick man, or a dying man, but for the ſouls of men a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctually deceaſed. Certainly this prayer muſt have refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, either to the ſleeping of the ſouls, or to the pains of Hell; To deliverance out of Purgatory it can have no relation. Neither are you a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to produce any one pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er publike or private, Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther any one indulgence to that purpoſe, for the delivery of any one ſoul out of Purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory, in all the Primitive
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:170067:82"/>
times, or out of your own antient Miſſals or records. Such are the Innovations which you would impoſe up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us, as Articles of Faith, which the greateſt part of the Catholick Church never received untill this day. Moreover though the ſins of the faithfull be privately and particularly remitted at the day of death, yet the publike promulgation of their pardon at the day of judgement is to come. Though their ſouls be alwaies in an eſtate of bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedneſs, yet they want the conſummation of this bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedneſs, extenſively at leaſt, untill the body be reunited unto the ſoul, (and as it is piouſly and probably belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved) intenſively alſo, that the
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:170067:83"/>
ſoul hath not yet ſo full and clear a viſion of God, as it ſhall have hereafter. Then what forbids Chriſtians to pray for this publick acquit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall, for this Conſummation of bleſſedneſs? So we do pray, as often as we ſay, <hi>thy kingdom come,</hi> or <hi>come Lord Jeſus, come quickly,</hi> Our Church is yet plainer, <hi>that we with this our Brother, and all other departed in the faith of thy holy name, may have our perfect Conſumma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of bleſſedneſs in thy eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall kingdom.</hi> This is far e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough from your more gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full prayers for the dead, to deliver them out of Purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of the Pope.</note>Laſtly, concerning the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of the Pope, It is he
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:170067:83"/>
himſelf that hath renounced his lawfull Patriarchall Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority. And if we ſhould offer it him at this day, he would diſdain it. We have only freed our ſelves from his tyrannicall uſurped Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity. But upon what termes, upon what grounds, how far, and with what intention, we have ſeparated our ſelves, or rather have ſuffered our ſelves to be ſeparated from the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> you may find if you pleaſe in the Treatiſe of Schiſm.</p>
               <p>I cannot chooſe but won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to ſee you cite St. <hi>Cypri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> againſt us in this caſe,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>P</hi> 27.</note> who ſeparated himſelf from you, as well as we, in the dayes of a much better Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop than we, and upon
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:170067:84"/>
much weaker grounds than we, and publiſhed his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to the world in two A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frican Councils; He liked not the ſwelling title of Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of Biſhops, nor that one Biſhop ſhould tyrannically terrifie an other into obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence; No more do we. He gave a primacy, or principa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of order to the Chair of St. <hi>Peter</hi> as <hi>principi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m unita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis;</hi> ſo do we: But he belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved that every Biſhop, had an equall ſhare of Epiſcopall power; ſo do we. He provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded a part, as he thought fit in a Provinciall Councill for his own ſafety, and the ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of his flock; ſo did we. He writ to your great Biſhop as to his Brother and Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legue, and dared to reprehend
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:170067:84"/>
him for receiving but a let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter from ſuch as had been cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured by the African Biſhops. In St. <hi>Cyprians</hi> ſenſe, you are the beam that have ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parated your ſelves from the body of the Sun; you are the Bough that is lopped from the Tree; you are the ſtream which is divided from the Fountain. It is you, princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally you, that have divided the unity of the Church.</p>
               <p>You collect as a Corolla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry from our ſuppoſed princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall of the right and ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ency of private judgement,<note place="margin">Whether humane Laws bynd the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience.</note> inlightned by the Spirit, that no humane Authority can bind the conſcience of an o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, or preſcribe any thing unto it. I have formerly ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed you your groſs miſtake in
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:170067:85"/>
the premiſes, Now if you pleaſe hear our ſenſe of the Concluſion. Humane Laws cannot be properly ſaid to bind the Conſcience, by the ſole authority of the Law-giver, But partly by the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity of the Law, every one being obliged to advance that which conduceth to a pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick good, <hi>thou ſhalt love thy neighbour as thy ſelf;</hi> And eſpecially by divine Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, which commands <hi>every ſoul to be ſubject to the higher powers; for conſcience ſake;</hi> not prudentially only. The queſtion is ſoon decided, juſt Laws of lawfull Superiors, either Civill; or Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call, have authority to bind the conſcience in themſelves, but not from themſelves.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="165" facs="tcp:170067:85"/>How ſhall we beleeve that <hi>it is not you but God that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſents theſe things to his Majeſty,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">P. 34. 69. The Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Enthu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticall.</note> 
                  <hi>that addreſſeth them to him by your mouth, that calleth him, that ſtret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth out his hand to him, that hath ſet theſe things be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his eyes, in Characters not to be defaced.</hi> What? That his Majeſty ſhould turn Roman Catholick? Are they like <hi>Belſhazars</hi> Characters; and are you the only <hi>Daniel</hi> that can read them? we do not ſee a <hi>Cloven tongue</hi> upon your head, nor a <hi>Dove</hi> ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming to whiſper in your ear. Be not too confident left ſome take it to be a little taint of Anabaptiſm, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps you have had as ſtrange phantaſies as this heretofore,
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:170067:86"/>
whilſt you were of a contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry party.</p>
               <p>Be it what it will be, you cannot offer it to his Majeſty with more confidence, or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend more intimacy with God, or to be more familiarly acquainted with his Cabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net Counſail, than a Scotch Presbyter; And yet your ſelf would not value all his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence at a Button. Wiſe men are not eaſily gained by empty ſhews or pretenſes, that ſignifie nothing but the pretenders vanity, nor by en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thuſiaſticall interpretation of occurrences. It is onely the weight of reaſon that depreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth the ſcale of their judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and makes them to yield and ſubmit unto it.</p>
               <p>Howſoever it be God or
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:170067:86"/>
you that repreſent theſe things to his Majeſty, you tell us that the <hi>end is to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce him from thoſe errors which he ſucked in with his milk, which in the dayes of peace, and abundance, it had been difficult for him to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover. But now his eyes and his ears do ſee and hear thoſe truths which make it evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent to him, that God hath condemned them to reduce him to the Communion of the Church;</hi> wherein you promiſe him all manner of bleſſings. Who told you of his Majeſties new Illumina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion? or what have you ſeen to beleeve any ſuch thing? when you dare avouch ſuch groſs untruths of himſelf, to himſelf, how ſhould he credit
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:170067:87"/>
your private preſumptions, which you tell him as a new <hi>Mercury</hi> dropped down from Heaven.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maniſts require ſubmiſſion to their Church as neceſſary to ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</note>You tell us that it is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for every one <hi>to adhere to the true Church, which is the keeper of ſaving truth.</hi> That is true, but nothing to his Majeſty, who hath more right already in the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Church than your ſelf. You tell us moreover that this Church is <hi>the Roman Church.</hi> That is not true; but ſuppoſe it were moſt true, as it is moſt falſe, what ſhould a man be better or nearer to the knowledge of the truth, and conſequently to his ſalvation, for his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to the Roman Church;<note place="margin">Yet can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not agree among themſelves what this Roman Church is.</note> As long as you cannot a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:170067:87"/>
among your ſelves, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther what this Roman Church is, or what your in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible Judge is? One ſaith it is the Pope alone; Another ſaith no, but the Pope with his Conclave of Cardinals; A third will goe no leſs than the Pope and a Provinciall Councill; A fourth will not be contented without the Pope and a generall Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cill; A fifth is for a Generall Councill alone either with, or without the Pope; A ſixth party, (and they are of no ſmall eſteem among you here at this preſent,) is for the eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentiall Church, that is the Company of all faithfull people, whoſe reception (ſay they,) makes the true ratifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of the Acts of its re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentative
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:170067:88"/>
body. It were as good to have no infallible Judge, as not to know or a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree who it is? Be not ſo cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious in condemning others, for not ſubmitting to your Roman Church or infallible Judge, nor ſo poſitive to make this ſubmiſſion ſo abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely neceſſary to ſalvation, untill you agree better what this Judge or Church is. It is five to one againſt you, that you your ſelf miſs the right Judge.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The Engliſh Church not peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed.</note>Whatſoever become of your Church, you ſay <hi>Ours is pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed by the proper Axioms of our own Reformation, and hath no more any ſubſiſtence in the world, nor pretence to the Privilege of a Church.</hi> This is hard. He periſheth
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:170067:88"/>
twice that periſheth by his own weapons. Even ſo <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſephs</hi> Brethren told <hi>Joſeph</hi> himſelf with Conſciences guilty enough, <hi>One is not:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 42.13.</note> This is that which the Court of <hi>Rome</hi> would be content to purchaſe at any rate. This hath been the end of all then ſecret Negotiations and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions, by all means to ſupport the Presbyterian fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction in <hi>England</hi> againſt E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopacy; Not that they lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved them more than us, but that they feared us more than them.</p>
               <p>There was an Iſraelitiſh Church, when <hi>Elias</hi> did not ſee it; but he muſt be as blind as <hi>Bartimaeus,</hi> that cannot ſee the Engliſh Church. Whereſoever there is a law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:170067:89"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="171" facs="tcp:170067:89"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="172" facs="tcp:170067:90"/>
Engliſh Paſtor, and an Engliſh Flock, and a ſubor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination of this Flock to that Paſtor, there is a branch of the true Engliſh Proteſtant Church. Do you make no difference between a Church perſecuted, and a Church ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſhed? Have patience and expect the Cataſtrophe. It may be all this while the <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penters Son</hi> is making a Cof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fin for <hi>Julian.</hi> If it pleaſe God, we may yet ſee the Church of <hi>England</hi> which is now fry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the fire, come out like Gold out of the Furnace, more pure, and more full of luſtre. If not, his will be done. <hi>Juſt art thou O Lord, and righteous are all thy iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</hi> The Primitive Church was as glorious in the ſight
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:170067:90"/>
of God when they ſerved him in Holes and Corners, in <hi>Cryptis, Sacellis, conven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulis, eccleſiolis,</hi> as when his worſhip was more ſplendid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly performed in <hi>Baſilicis,</hi> and <hi>Cyriacis,</hi> in goodly Churches, and magnificent Cathedrals.</p>
               <p>Your deſign ſtops not at the King of great <hi>Britain,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>P.</hi> 42.</note> but extends it ſelf <hi>to all his ſubjects,</hi> yea <hi>to all Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants</hi> whatſoever. I won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der why you ſtay there,<note place="margin">The Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors vain dreams.</note> and would not adde all the Ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtern Churches, and the great Turk himſelf, ſince you might have done it with one other penfull of Ink? and with as much pretence of reaſon, to ſecure himſelf from the joynt forces of Chriſtendom thus u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nited by your means. A
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:170067:91"/>
ſtrong phantaſie will diſcover Armies, and Navies in the Clouds, men and horſes, and chariots in the fire, and hear articulate dictates from the Bels. This is not to write waking, but dreaming.</p>
               <p>Yet you make it an eaſy work, <hi>to effect which there needs no diſputation, but onely to behold the Hereticall Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius of our Reformation,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">P. 43. 44.</note> 
                  <hi>which is ſufficiently condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by it ſelf, if men will onely take the pains to compare the fundamentall principles there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of with the Conſequences.</hi> Great Houſes and Forts are builded at an eaſy charge in Paper. When you have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulted with your Architects and Engeniers, you will find it to be a work of more dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty.
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:170067:91"/>
And your adverſaries reſolution may teach you to your coſt, what it is to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe your ſelf ſuch an eaſie conqueſt before the fight, and let you ſee that thoſe golden mountains which you phantaſied have no ſubſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance but in your own brain, and ſend you home to ſeek out that ſelf-conviction there, which you ſought to faſten upon others. When you are able to prove your Univerſall Monarchy, your new Canon of Faith, your new Treaſury of the Church, your new Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Purgatory whereof the Pope keeps the Keys, your Image worſhip, your com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon prayers in a tongue un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known, your deteining of the Cup from the Laity in
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:170067:92"/>
the publike adminiſtration of the Sacrament, and the reſt of your new Creed, out of the four firſt Generall Councils, or the Univerſall Tradition of the Church in thoſe dayes, either as principles or funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall truths, (which you affirm,) or ſo much as ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary points of faith, (which we deny,) we will yield our ſelves to be guilty both of Contradiction and Schiſm. Untill you are able to make theſe innovations good, it were beſt for you to be ſilent, and leave your vapouring. Deſperate undertakings do eaſily forfeit a mans reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.<note place="margin">P. 47. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> His vainer propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Now are we come to the moſt ſpecious piece of your whole Epiſtle, that is <hi>the
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:170067:92"/>
motion or propoſition of a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference, by Authority of the King of</hi> France, <hi>at the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of the King of great</hi> Britain, <hi>before the Arch-Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of</hi> Paris, <hi>and his Coad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jutor, between ſome of your Roman Catholick Doctors, and the Miniſters of the reformed Church at</hi> Paris, whom you do deſervedly commend for their ſufficiency and zeal. You further ſuppoſe that <hi>the Miniſters of the reformed Church will accept of ſuch a diſputation, or by their Tergi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation betray the weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of their cauſe;</hi> And you conclude confidently beyond ſuppoſition, <hi>that they will be confuted and convicted, and that their converſion or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction will afford ſufficient
<pb n="178" facs="tcp:170067:93"/>
ground to the King of great</hi> Britain, <hi>to embrace the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of the Roman Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Church; And that his converſion will reduce all conſcientious Proteſtants to unity and due obedience.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I will contract your larger Palm to a Fiſt. If the King of great <hi>Britain</hi> deſire a ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn conference, the King of <hi>France</hi> will enjoyn it; If he injoyn it, the Miniſters will accept; if they do accept it, they are ſure to be convi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted; if they be convicted, the King of great <hi>Britain</hi> will change his Religion; if hee change his Religion, all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcientious Proteſtants will be reduced: And all this to be done, not by the old way of diſputing, No, take heed of
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:170067:93"/>
that, the burn'd child dreads the fire; But by a proper new way of refuting old Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant principles, by new In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dependent practiſes. Why was this Remedy found out no ſooner? This might have ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the Cardinals in their Conſultations about propa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gating the Faith; This might have ſaved Cardinall <hi>Allen</hi> all his Machiavillian Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions to his Engliſh Emiſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries; This may in a ſhort time turn the Inquiſitors out of their employment, for want of an Object, and not leave ſuch a thing as hereticall pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity in the world. How muſt men praiſe your fortune, and applaud your Invention? But ſtay, the ſecond thoughts are wiſer; What if this Chain
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:170067:94"/>
ſuppoſed to be of Adamant, ſhould prove a rope of ſand? And ſo it is; I have ſeen a <hi>Sorites</hi> diſgraced, and hiſſed out of the Schools, for drawing but one lame leg after it. This is foundred of all four, from the beginning to the end there is nothing in it but fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Contingents, which are known onely to God, not one grain of neceſſary truth.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The King of <hi>England</hi> deſires no ſuch Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference.</note>Firſt Sir, be not angry if a man take away the ſubject of your whole diſcourſe; It is but your officiouſneſs, the King deſires no ſuch Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence. Let them deſire Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences who waver in their faith. All theſe bluſtering ſtorms have radicated him dee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per in his Religion. And chiefly that which you make
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:170067:94"/>
the chiefeſt motive to his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtating, the Martyrdom of his royall Father, and an he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reditary love to that Church which he hath juſtified with his blood.</p>
               <p>Secondly,<note place="margin">If he ſhould, he had nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon nor need to deſert his Engliſh Clergy.</note> if his Majeſty ſhould encline to ſuch a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference, do you think he would deſert the Engliſh Clergy, who have forſaken their Country, their Friends, their Eſtates, out of their Conſcience, out of their duty to God, and their Soveraign, who underſtand the Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of the Engliſh Church much better than your ſelf, or any Foreiners how ſufficient ſoever, and caſt himſelf whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly upon ſtrangers, whoſe Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation (you ſay) is diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent from that of <hi>England,</hi>
                  <pb n="182" facs="tcp:170067:95"/>
in the points of Epiſcopacy, Liturgy, and the Ceremonies of the Church? Say, what was the Reaſon of this groſs Omiſſion? were you afraid of <hi>that Image of the Church</hi> (as you call it in a ſleighting manner) which they reteined? Or did you not think any of the Engliſh Nation worthy to bear your books at a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference? It hath been other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe heretofore, and you will find it otherwiſe now, when you come to prove it. I know not whether <hi>England</hi> hath been more fortunate or unfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate ſince the Reformation, in breeding as many able Polemique writers on both ſides, as any Nation in <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope; Stapleton, Harding, Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, Sanders, Reynolds, Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop.</hi>
                  <pb n="183" facs="tcp:170067:95"/>
&amp;c. for the Roman Church. <hi>Jewell, Andrews, Abbot, Laewd, White, Field, Montague, Reynolds, Whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taker,</hi> &amp;c. for the Engliſh Church (I forbear to name thoſe that are living) And ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny more who come not ſhort of theſe, if they had pleaſed to communicate their Talents to the world. This is ſuch a Contumely as reflects upon the Nation, and you muſt be content to be told of it.</p>
               <p>Thirdly,<note place="margin">Such a Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence not fit to be granted by the King of <hi>France.</hi>
                  </note> how are you ſure that the King of <hi>France</hi> and his Counſell would give way to ſuch a ſolemn and publique Conference? private Inſinuati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons uſe to prevail much when a man may <hi>Laevere &amp; tack</hi> to and again to compaſs his ends. Authority or the Sword may
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:170067:96"/>
put an end to Controverſies: But publick Conferences for the moſt part do but ſtart new Queſtions, and revive old forgotten animoſities. What were the <hi>Donatiſts</hi> the better for the <hi>Collation</hi> at <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thage?</hi> The mind of a man is generous, and where it looks for oppoſition, fortifies it ſelf againſt it. <hi>Urban</hi> the Eighth was the wiſeſt Pope you have had of late, who by his moderation and courteſie cooled much of that <hi>heat,</hi> which the violence of his Predeceſſors had raiſed againſt the <hi>Court</hi> of <hi>Rome.</hi> The mild beams of the Sun were more prevalent, than the blu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtering blaſts of the North wind. Multiplying of words more commonly engenders
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:170067:96"/>
ſtrife, than peace.</p>
               <p>Fourthly,<note place="margin">Nor to be accepted by the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed Church.</note> upon what grounds are you ſo confident, that the Miniſters of the Reformed Church would admit of ſuch a publick Diſputation upon thoſe terms which you pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe? That, is to accept of the Archbiſhop of <hi>Paris</hi> and his Coadjutor, two perſons in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſſed, for competent Judges. I am as confident of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, that they would rather chuſe to ſuffer, than wrong their cauſe ſo much; <hi>Fruſtra fit per plura quod fieri poteſt per pauciora.</hi> It were a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier way for them, and but the ſame in effect, to ſubſcribe to a blank paper, and to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit without diſputation.<note place="margin">Nor could any ſuch Succeſs be expected from it.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Fifthly, ſuppoſe (all this notwithſtanding) ſuch a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:170067:97"/>
ſhould hold, what reaſon have you to promiſe to your ſelf ſuch ſucceſs, as to obtain ſo eaſie a Victory? You have had Conferences and Conferences again at <hi>Poiſsye,</hi> and other places, and gained by them, juſt as much as you might put in your eye, and ſee never the worſe. When Conferences are onely made uſe of as <hi>Pageants,</hi> to grace the <hi>Introduction</hi> of ſome new <hi>Proſelyte,</hi> and to preſerve his <hi>Reputation</hi> from the aſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of deſultorious <hi>Levity,</hi> they ſeem much more effica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious than they are. As they know well enough who are privie to what is acted in the withdrawing room. The time was when you have been as confident in a contrary Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion,
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:170067:97"/>
that ſuch a free Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence would have ſealed the Walls of <hi>Rome,</hi> and levelled the Popes Triple Crown.</p>
               <p>Sixtly,<note place="margin">The Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinence and ſauci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs with the King.</note> whether the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters ſhould accept of ſuch a partiall unequall Conference or not, or whatſoever ſhould be the ſucceſs thereof, you treſpaſs too boldly upon his Majeſties patience, to dictate to him ſo pragmatically, ſo magiſterially, what he ſhould do, or would do, in ſuch a caſe, which is never like to be. Doth his Fathers con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy encourage you to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, that He is <hi>a Reed ſhaken with the wind; Qui pauca conſiderat, facile pronunciat,</hi> He that weighs no more cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances or occurrences than ſerve for the Advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:170067:98"/>
of his deſign, pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth ſentence eaſily, but teme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rariouſly, and for the moſt part unſoundly. When ſuch a thing as you dream of ſhould happen, it were good man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners in you to leave his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty to his Chriſtian Liberty. But to trouble your ſelf and others about the Moons ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in the water, ſo unſeaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nably, ſo impertinently, or with what will come to paſs when the sky falls, is unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeming the Counſeller of a King.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">His Pen over <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uns his wit.</note>Laſtly, conſider how your pen doth over-run your rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and over-reach all grounds of probability, to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe unto his Majeſties change ſuch an infallible In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence upon all Proteſtants,
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:170067:98"/>
as to reduce them to the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Communion, not onely his own ſubjects, but forei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners. His bleſſed Fathers ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample had not ſo much influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence upon the Scots his native Subjects. He was no Change<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling indeed, neither to the right hand, nor to the left. <hi>Henry</hi> the Fourth his Grand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>father, did turn indeed to the Roman Church. Had his change any ſuch Influence upon the Proteſtant party in <hi>France?</hi> I know no follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers ſuch a change would gain him, but I foreſee clearly how many hearts it would loſe him. Certainly Sir, if you would do a meritorious piece of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2+ letters">
                     <desc>••…</desc>
                  </gap>ice to his greateſt Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries, you could not fix upon any thing that would
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:170067:99"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="189" facs="tcp:170067:99"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="190" facs="tcp:170067:100"/>
content them more highly, than to ſee you ſucceſsfull in this undertaking. I have done with your Propoſition. Hee than compares it and your de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtration together, will ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily judge them to be twins at the firſt ſight.</p>
               <p>As a motive to his Majeſties converſion, you preſent him with a Treatiſe of Tranſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiation, and deſire that <hi>it may appear unto the world under his royall name.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>P.</hi> 58.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">His im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proper choiſe of a Patron for his Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe.</note>I meddle not with your Treatiſe, ſome of your lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Adverſaries friends will give you your hands full e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough. But how can his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty protect or patroniſe a Treatiſe againſt his Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, againſt his Conſcience, ſo contrary to the doctrine of
<pb n="191" facs="tcp:170067:100"/>
the Church of <hi>England,</hi> not onely ſince the Reformation, but before? About the year ſeven hundred,<note place="margin">Serm. Sax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. in feſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Paſchat.</note> 
                  <hi>The body of Chriſt wherein he ſuffered, and his Body Conſecrated in the Host, differ much. The body wherein he ſuffred was born of the Virgin, conſiſting of fleſh and bones, and humane members; his Spirituall body, which we call the Host, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſists of many grains, without blood, bones, or human mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, wherefore nothing is to be underſtood there corporally, but all ſpiritually.</hi> Tranſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiation was neither held for an Article of Faith, nor a point of Faith in thoſe dayes.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>You charge the Proteſtants in divers places,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>P.</hi> 62.</note> 
                  <hi>That they
<pb n="192" facs="tcp:170067:101"/>
have neither Church nor Faith, but have loſt both.</hi> And at the later end of your Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe you undertake to demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate it:<note place="margin">P. 222.</note> 
                  <note place="margin">His un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>skilfulnes, or his un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in his Demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrations.</note> But your demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration is a meer Paralo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſm. You multiply your terms, you confound your terms, you change and alter your terms, contrary to the rules of right arguing, and vainly beat the air, conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding nothing which you ought to prove, nothing which your Adverſary will denie. You would prove that Proteſtants have no Church. That you never attempt; But you do attempt to prove (how pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifully God knows,) that they are not the onely Church, that is, <hi>the one, Holy Catholique Church.</hi> This they did never
<pb n="193" facs="tcp:170067:101"/>
affirm, they did never think. It ſufficeth them to be a part of that Univerſall Church, more pure, more Orthodox, more Catholique than the Roman, alwayes profeſſing Chriſt viſibly, never lurking inviſibly in an other Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, which is another of your miſtakes. I ſhould adviſe you to promiſe us no more <hi>evident demonſtrations;</hi> Either your skill, or your luck is ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremely bad.</p>
               <p>In the ſecond place you af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm that <hi>Faith is founded upon divine Authority, and Revelation, and depoſited with the Church.</hi> All that is true; But that which you add, that <hi>it is founded in the Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Chriſt ſpeaking by the mouth of his Church;</hi> By this
<pb n="194" facs="tcp:170067:102"/>
Church, underſtanding the Church of this Age, and (which is yet worſe) the Church of one place, and (which is worſt of all) the Biſhop of that one Church, is moſt falſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The great advantage of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove the Roman Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique in the choiſe of his foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note>And ſo is that which you add, that <hi>the faith of Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants is founded upon their own reaſonings, which makes ſo many differences among them.</hi> Reaſon muſt be ſubſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vient in the application of the Rule of Faith. It cannot be the foundation of Faith. Bad reaſoning may bring forth dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences and errors about Faith, both with you and us, but the abuſe of Reaſon doth not take away the uſe of Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. We have this Advantage of you, that if any one of us
<pb n="195" facs="tcp:170067:102"/>
do build an erroneous Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on upon the holy Scripture, yet becauſe our adherence to the Scripture is firmer and neerer than our adherence to our particular error, that full, and free, and univerſall aſſent which we give to holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and to all things therein conteined, is an implicite Condemnation and retracta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our particular error, which we hold unwittingly, and unwillingly againſt Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. But your foundation of Faith being compoſed of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certainties, whether this man be Pope or not, whether this Pope be Judge or not, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther this Judge be infallible or not, and if infallible, wherein, and how far; the faith which is builded there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon
<pb n="196" facs="tcp:170067:103"/>
cannot but be fallible and uncertain. The ſtricter the adherence is to a falſe, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certain, or fallible rule, the more dangerous is the error. So our right foundation purge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth away our error in ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction; And your wrong foundation leſſens the value of your truths, and doubles the guilt of your errors.</p>
               <p>I will (by your leave) requite your demonſtration, and turn the mouthes of your own Canons againſt your ſelf.</p>
               <p>That Church which hath changed the Apoſtolical Creed, the Apoſtolicall Succeſſion, the Apoſtolicall Regiment, and the Apoſtolicall Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, is no Apoſtolicall, Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodox, or Catholique Church.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="197" facs="tcp:170067:103"/>But the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> hath changed the Apoſtolicall Creed, the Apoſtolicall Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion, the Apoſtolicall Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giment, and the Apoſtolicall Communion.</p>
               <p>Therefore the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is no Apoſtolicall, Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodox, or Catholick Church.</p>
               <p>They have changed the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtolicall Creed, by making a new Creed, wherein are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny things inſerted, that hold no Analogie with the old A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles Creed; The Apoſtoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Succeſſion, by ingroſſing the whole ſucceſſion to <hi>Rome,</hi> and making all other Biſhops to be but the Popes Vicars, and Subſtitutes, as to their Juriſdiction; The Apoſtolicall Regiment by erecting a viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and Univerſall Monarchy
<pb n="198" facs="tcp:170067:104"/>
in the Church; And laſtly the Apoſtolicall Communion, by excommunicating three parts of the holy Catholique Apoſtolique Church.</p>
               <p>Again, That Church which reſolves its Faith not into di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Revelation and Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, but into Humane infalli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility, or the Infallibilitie of the preſent Church, without knowing, or according, what that preſent Church is, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Virtuall, or the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentative, or the eſſentiall Church, or a body compoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of ſome of theſe, hath no true faith.</p>
               <p>But the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> reſolves it Faith, not into di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dine Revelation and Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, but into the Infallibility of the preſent Church, not
<pb n="199" facs="tcp:170067:104"/>
knowing or not according what that preſent Church is, whether the Virtual Church (that is the Pope,) or the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentative Church (that is a generall Councill) or the Eſſentiall Church, (that is the Church of Believers diffu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed over the world,) or a body compounded of ſome of theſe, (that is the Pope, and a Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall or Provinciall Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cill.)</p>
               <p>Therefore the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> hath not true faith. The greater number of your Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters is for the Pope, that this infallibility is fixed to this Chair. But of all other Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, this is moſt fallible and uncertain, for if Simony make a Nullity in a Papall Election, we have great rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon
<pb n="200" facs="tcp:170067:105"/>
to doubt, that that Chair hath not been filled by a right Pope theſe laſt hundred years. Theſe are no other but your own <hi>Mediums;</hi> Such luck you have with your <hi>irrefra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gable demonſtrations.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">P. 68. His Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtacy is not the way to his reſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note>
                  <hi>In caſe his Majeſty will turn Roman Catholique you promiſe him reſtitution to his Kingdomes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Great undertakers are ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom good performers; when you are making your Proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lytes, you promiſe them gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Mountains, but when the work is done, you deal with them, as he did with his Saint, who promiſed a Candle as big as his Maſt, and offred one no bigger than his finger. Do you however think it reaſon, that any man ſhould change
<pb n="201" facs="tcp:170067:105"/>
his Religion for temporall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects, though it were for a Kingdom? <hi>Jeroboam</hi> did ſo, you may remember what was the ſucceſs of it.</p>
               <p>You propoſe this as <hi>the readieſt means to reſtore him.</hi> Others who penetrate deeper into the true ſtate of his af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs, look upon it as the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dieſt way to ruine his hopes, by the alienation of his friends, by the confirmation of his foes, and in ſome ſort the juſtification of their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer feigned fears. Do you think all Roman Catholique Princes deſire this change as earneſtly as your ſelf? Give them leave firſt to conſult with their particular Intereſts. A common Intereſt prevails more with Confederates than
<pb n="202" facs="tcp:170067:106"/>
a common faith. The Sword diſtinguiſheth not between Proteſtants and Papiſts.</p>
               <p>But what is the ground of this your great Confidence? no leſs than Scripture. <hi>Seek ye firſt the kingdom of God, and the righteouſneſs of it, and all other things ſhall be added unto you.</hi> You ſay the word of God deceives no man. True, but you may de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive your ſelf out of the word of God. The Concluſion al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes follows the weaker part, ſuch as this, are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly your miſtaken grounds, when they come to be exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned. The text ſaith, <hi>Seek the kingdom of God,</hi> You would have his Majeſty deſert the kingdom of God; The promiſe is of all things neceſſary or
<pb n="203" facs="tcp:170067:106"/>
convenient, you will be your own Carver, and oblige God Almighty to Kingdoms and particular conditions; The promiſe is made (as all tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall promiſes are,) with an implicite exception of the Croſs, unleſs God ſee it to be otherwiſe more expedient for us; He that denies us gold, and gives us patience and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther graces <hi>more precious than Gold,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Pet. 1.7.</note> that denies a temporall Kingdom to give an eternall, doth not wrong us. This was out of your head.</p>
               <p>That the Scots had an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tienter <hi>Obligation to fidelity</hi> towards his Majeſty,<note place="margin">P. 70. The obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of the Scots to his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty the greateſt of any Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects in the known world.</note> and that Royall Family than the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh, is a truth not to be doubted or diſputed of, I think I may ſafely adde, than
<pb n="204" facs="tcp:170067:107"/>
any Nation in <hi>Europe,</hi> or in the known world to their Prince, his Majeſty being the hundred and tenth Monarch of that line, that hath ſweyed the Scepter of that Kingdom ſucceſſively. The more the pitty that a few treacherous <hi>Shebas,</hi> and a pack of baw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling ſeditious Orators, under the vizard and ſhadow of pure Religion, to the extreme ſcandall of all honeſt profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors, ſhould be able to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn ſuch an antient fabrick, and radicated ſucceſſion of Kingly Government.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Their Treachery</note>But take heed Sir, how you beleeve that any ingagement of the Presbyterian faction in <hi>Scotland,</hi> proceeded either from conſcience, or grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude, or fidelity, or aimed at
<pb n="205" facs="tcp:170067:107"/>
the reſetling of his Majeſty upon his throne. No, no, their hearts were double, their treaties on their parts were meer treacheries from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning. I mean not any of thoſe many loyall patriots, that never bowed their knees to <hi>Baal-berith the God of the Covenant,</hi> in that Nation:<note place="margin">The loyall Scots ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted.</note> Nor yet any of thoſe ſerious converts, that no ſooner diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered the <hi>leger de main</hi> of a company of <hi>canting impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors,</hi> but they ſought to ſtop the ſtream of Schiſm and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, with the hazard of their own lives and eſtates. Nor even thoſe whoſe eyes were longer held with the Spirit of ſlumber, by ſome ſtronger ſpels of diſciplina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian charmers, but did yet
<pb n="206" facs="tcp:170067:108"/>
later open their eyes, and come in to do their duties, at the ſixth or ninth hour. All theſe are expunged by me out of this black Roll. Let their poſterities enjoy the fruit of their reſpective loyalties, And let their memories be daily more and more bleſſed. But I mean the obſtinate Ring-leaders,<note place="margin">The diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loyall Scots de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciphered.</note> and Standard-bearers of the Presbyterian <hi>Covenant</hi> of both robes, and the ſetters up of that miſhapen <hi>Idoll.</hi> It is from theſe I ſay, that no help or hope could in reaſon be expected. They who ſold the Father, and ſuch a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, were not likely to proove loyall to the Son. They who hanged up one of the moſt antient Gentlemen in <hi>Europe,</hi> the gallant <hi>Marqueſs of Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troſe,</hi>
                  <pb n="207" facs="tcp:170067:108"/>
being then their law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Vice-roy, like a dog in ſuch baſe and barbarous man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, together with his <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Commiſſion,</hi> to the publike diſhonour of their King, in the chief <hi>City</hi> of that Kingdom, in a time of <hi>Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty;</hi> They who purged the Army, over and over, as loth on their parts willingly to leave one dram of honeſty, or loyalty in it, who would not admit their fellow ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of much more merit and courage than themſelves to aſſiſt them; They who would not permit his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty to continue among the Souldiery, leſt hee ſhould grow too popular; They who after they had proclamed to the world his Title and right
<pb n="208" facs="tcp:170067:109"/>
to that Crown, yet ſought to have him excluded from the benefit of it, and from the execution of his Kingly Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>P.</hi> 70.</note> untill he ſhould <hi>abjure his Religion, caſt dirt upon his Parents, alienate his loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all ſubiects, and ratifie the aſurpations of his Rebels;</hi> Theſe, (there I ſay,) were moſt unlikely perſons to be his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorers. Was it ever heard be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, that ſubjects acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged a Soveraign, and yet endeavoured to exclude him from his rights, untill he had granted whatſoever ſeemed good in their eyes?<note place="margin">No hope from that party un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till they repent.</note> Others may be more ſevere in their judgements, but I for my part could be well contented, that God would give them the Honour to be the repay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers
<pb n="209" facs="tcp:170067:109"/>
of the breach, who have been the makers of the breach; to be the reſtorers of Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy, who have been the rui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners of Monarchy; to be the re-eſtabliſhers of peace, who have been the chiefeſt <hi>Cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lines</hi> and promoters of War. But that can never be whilſt they juſtifie their former re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellious practiſes, and after they have eaten and devou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, <hi>wipe their mouths, and ſay what have we done?</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till they acknowledge their former errors; Repentance onely is able to knit the bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken bone; why ſhould they be more afraid to confeſs their faults, and ſhame the Devill, than to commit them?<note place="margin">
                     <hi>P.</hi> 73. God muſt not be li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mited to time or means of delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Yet I cannot ſay with you that this <hi>hath robbed his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty
<pb n="210" facs="tcp:170067:110"/>
of all hopes and means of recovery.</hi> We may not limit God to any time, who com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly with-holds his help untill the Bricks be doubled, untill the edge of the razor doth touch the very throats of his ſervants, that the glory of the work may wholy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dound to himſelf. We may not limit God to thoſe means which ſeem moſt probable in our eyes. So long as <hi>Joſeph</hi> truſted to his friend in <hi>Court,</hi> God did forget him; when <hi>Pharaohs Butler</hi> had quite forgotten <hi>Joſeph,</hi> then God remembred him. God hath nobler wayes of reſtitution than by Battails, and bloud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, that is, by changing the hearts of his creatures at his pleaſure, and turning <hi>Eſau</hi>'s
<pb n="211" facs="tcp:170067:110"/>
vowed revenge into love and kindneſs.</p>
               <p>I confeſs,<note place="margin">P. 74. 75. His Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cape out of <hi>England</hi> almoſt mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raculous.</note> 
                  <hi>his Majeſties reſolution was great,</hi> ſo was his prudence, that neither fear <hi>(which uſeth to betray the ſuccours of the Soul,)</hi> nor any indiſcreet Action, or word, or geſture, in ſo long a time ſhould either diſcover him, or render him ſuſpected. When I conſider that the Heir of a Crown, in the midſt of that Kingdom where he had his breeding, whom all mens eyes had uſed to Court as the riſing Sun, of no com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon features or phyſiogno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, at ſuch time when he was not onely believed, but known to be among them, when every Corner of the Kingdom was full of Spys to
<pb n="212" facs="tcp:170067:111"/>
ſearch him, and every Port and Inne full of Officers to apprehend him, I ſay that he ſhould travail at ſuch a time, ſo long, ſo far, ſo freely, in the ſight of the Sun, expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to the view of all per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, without either diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, or ſuſpition, ſeeme little leſs than a miracle. That God had ſmitten the eyes of thoſe who met him with blindneſs, as the eyes of the <hi>Sodomites,</hi> that they could not find <hi>Lots</hi> door, or the <hi>Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian</hi> Souldiers, that were ſent to apprehend <hi>Eliſha.</hi> This ſtrange eſcape, and that for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer out of <hi>Scotland,</hi> where his condition was not much better,<note place="margin">And ſeems to preſage that God hath ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to do with him.</note> nor his perſon much ſafer, do ſeem ſtrangely to preſage, that God hath yet
<pb n="213" facs="tcp:170067:111"/>
ſome great work, to be done by him in his own due time.</p>
               <p>You attribute this rare de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>P.</hi> 76. Prayers and tears the proper Arms of woman,</note> and the hopes of his converſion, in part <hi>to the prayers and tears of his Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; prayers and tears</hi> were the onely proper Arms of the old Primitive Chriſtians; more particularly they are the beſt and moſt agreeable defence of that ſex; but eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially the prayers and tears of a Mother, for the <hi>Son of her deſires,</hi> are moſt powerfull. As it was ſaid of the prayers and tears of <hi>Monica,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eſpecially of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers;</note> for St. <hi>Auſtine</hi> her Son; <hi>fieri non potuit ut filius iſtarum lacry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marum periret,</hi> It could not be that a Son ſhould periſh for whom ſo many tears were
<pb n="214" facs="tcp:170067:112"/>
ſhed. God ſees her <hi>tears,</hi> and hears her <hi>prayers,</hi> and will grant her requeſt, if not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to her will and deſire, (we often ask thoſe things which being granted would prove prejudiciall to our ſelves and our friends) yet <hi>ad uti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litatem,</hi> to his Majeſties grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter advantage, which is much better: She wiſheth him a good Catholick, and God will preſerve him a good Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick as he is. We do not doubt but the prayers of his Father <hi>(who now follows the Lamb in his whites)</hi> for his perſeverance,<note place="margin">Yet not ſo powerfull as his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terceſſion now in Heaven.</note> will be more ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectuall with God, than the prayers of his Mother for his change.<note place="margin">P. 77. The Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of <hi>Henry</hi> the great not pertinent.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Your inſtance of his <hi>Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties Grand-father,</hi> your grand
<pb n="215" facs="tcp:170067:112"/>
King <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth is not ſo appoſite, or fit for your purpoſe. He gained his Crown by turning himſelf towards his people, you would per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade his Majeſty to turn from his people, and to caſt away his poſſibilities of reſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution, that is,<note place="margin">Plutarch.</note> 
                  <hi>to cut off a naturall leg, and take one of wood.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>To the tears of his Mother you adde <hi>the blood of his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>P.</hi> 77. 78. The juſt commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of K. <hi>Charls.</hi>
                  </note> whom you juſtly ſtile <hi>happy,</hi> and ſay moſt truly of him, that <hi>he preferred the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Faith before his Crown, his liberty, his life, and whatſoever was moſt dear unto him.</hi> This faith was for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly rooted in his heart by God, <hi>not ſecretly and invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly in the laſt moments of
<pb n="216" facs="tcp:170067:113"/>
his life to unite him to the Roman Catholick Church,</hi> but openly during his whole Reign, all which time he li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in the boſom of the true Catholick Church.<note place="margin">It is groſs impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence to feign that he dyed a Roman Catholick.</note> Yet you are ſo extremely partiall to your ſelf, that you affirm that he <hi>died inviſibly</hi> a Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of your Roman Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Church, as it is by you contre-diſtinguiſhed to the reſt of the Chriſtian world. An old pious fraud, or artifice of yours, learned from <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiavell,</hi> to gain <hi>credit</hi> to your <hi>Religion</hi> by all means, either true or falſe; but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to his own profeſſion at his death, contrary to the expreſs knowledge of all that were preſent at his murther. Upon a vain preſumption,
<pb n="217" facs="tcp:170067:113" rendition="simple:additions"/>
that <hi>Talem niſi vestra Eccleſia nulla parerit fili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um.</hi> And becauſe you are not able to produce one li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving witneſs, you cite St. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtin</hi> to no purpoſe to prove that <hi>the elect before they are converted, do belong invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly to the Church;</hi> Yea and before they were born alſo. But St. <hi>Auſtine</hi> neither ſaid nor thought, that after they are converted they make no viſible profeſſion, or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs the contrary to that which they beleeve. Seek not thus to adorn your particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Church, not with <hi>barrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi> but with <hi>ſtollen Saints,</hi> Whom all the world know to have been none of yours. What Faith he profeſſed li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, he confirmed dying;
<pb n="218" facs="tcp:170067:114"/>
In the Communion of the Church of <hi>England</hi> he lived, and in that Communion at his death he commended his ſoul into the hands of God his Saviour.<note place="margin">The Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion confutes his demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration, that Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants have no faith.</note> That which you have confeſſed here concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning King <hi>Charls,</hi> will ſpoil your former demonſtration, <hi>that the Proteſtants have neither Church nor Faith.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But you confeſs no more in particular here, than I have heard ſome of your famous Roman Doctors in this City acknowledge to be true in generall; And no more than that which the Biſhop of <hi>Chalcedon</hi> (a man that can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be ſuſpected of partiality on our ſide,) hath affirmed and publiſhed in two of his Books to the world in Print;
<pb n="219" facs="tcp:170067:114"/>
That <hi>Protestantibus creden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>perſons living in the Communion of the Proteſtant Church, if they endeavour to learn the truth, and are not able to attein unto it, but hold it implicitely in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration of their minds, and are ready to receive it when God ſhall be pleaſed to reveal it</hi> (which all good Proteſtants and all good Chriſtians are) they <hi>neither want Church, nor Faith, nor Salvation.</hi> Mark theſe words well. They have neither <hi>Church nor Faith ſay you;</hi> If they be thus qualified (as they all are) they <hi>want neither Church, nor Faith, nor Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation</hi> (ſaith he.<note place="margin">His intel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence as good in Heaven as upon earth.</note>)</p>
               <p>Laſtly Sir, to let us ſee, that your intelligence is as good in Heaven as it is upon Earth, &amp;
<pb n="220" facs="tcp:170067:115"/>
that you know both who are there, and what they do, you tell us that the Crown and Conqueſt, which his late Majeſty gained by his ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings, was procured by the interceſſion of his Grand-Mother Queen <hi>Mary.</hi> We ſhould be the apter to beleeve this, if you were able to make it appear, that all the Saints in Heaven do know all the particular neceſſities of all their poſterity upon earth. St. <hi>Austin</hi> makes the matter much more doubtfull than you, that's the leaſt of his Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertion,<note place="margin">Aug. de cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra pro mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuus. c. <hi>15.</hi>
                  </note> or rather to be plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly falſe; <hi>fatendum eſt neſcire quidem mortuos quid hic a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatur.</hi> But with preſumpti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons you did begin your De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dication, and with preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
<pb n="221" facs="tcp:170067:115"/>
you end it. In the mean time till you can make that appear, we obſerve, that nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Queen <hi>Maries</hi> conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy in the Roman Catholick Faith,<note place="margin">No faith ſufficient armour a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt bloody attempts:</note> nor <hi>Henry</hi> the fourths change to the Roman Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Faith, could ſave them from a bloudy end. Then by what warrant do you impute King <hi>Charls</hi> his ſufferings to his error in Religion? Be your own Judge.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Heu quanta de ſpe decidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus;</hi> Alas!<note place="margin">The Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor much faln from his former charity in ſeeking the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>euni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendome.</note> from what hopes are we faln! Pardon our er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, that we have miſtaken you ſo long. You have here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore pretended your ſelf to be a moderate perſon, and one that ſeriouſly endevoured the reuniting of Chriſtendom by a fair Accommodation. The
<pb n="222" facs="tcp:170067:116"/>
wideſt wounds are cloſed up in time, and ſtrange Plants by inoculation are incorpora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted together, and made one; And is there no way to cloſe up the wounds of the Church, and to unite the diſagreeing members of the ſame myſticall body? Why were <hi>Caleb</hi> and <hi>Joſhua</hi> onely admitted into the Land of promiſe, whilſt the carkaſſes of the reſt pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed in the Wilderneſs, but onely becauſe they had been Peace-makers in a time of Schiſm? Well fare our learned and ingenuous Country-man <hi>S. Clara,</hi> who is altogether as perſpicacious as your ſelf, but much more charitable. You tell us to our grief,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>P.</hi> 204.</note> that <hi>there is no accommodation to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected; that Cardinall</hi> Riche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieu
<pb n="223" facs="tcp:170067:116"/>
                  <hi>was too good a Chriſtian, and too good a Catholique to have any ſuch thought; that the one Religion is true, the other falſe, and that there is no ſociety between light and darkneſs.</hi> This is plain dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, to tell us what we muſt truſt to. No Peace is to be expected from you, unleſs we will come unto you upon our knees, with the words of the <hi>Prodigall Child</hi> in our mouthes, <hi>Father forgive us. we have ſinned againſt Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and againſt thee.</hi> Is not this rare Courteſie? If we will ſubmit to your will in all things, you will have no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger difference with us. So we might come to ſhake a worſe Church by the hand, than that which we were ſeparated from.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="224" facs="tcp:170067:117"/>
                  <note place="margin">The way to a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Acco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modation.</note>If you could be contented to wave your laſt four hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred years determinations, or if you liked them for your ſelves, yet not to obtrude them upon other Churches; If you could reſt ſatisfied with your old <hi>Patriarchal power,</hi> and your <hi>Principium unitatis,</hi> or <hi>Primacy of Order,</hi> much good might be expected from free Councills, and Conferences from moderate perſons; And we might yet live in Hope to ſee an Union, if not in all O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions, yet in charity, and all neceſſary points of ſaving truth, between all Chriſtians; to ſee the <hi>Eastern</hi> and <hi>Weſtern</hi> Churches joyn hand in hand, and ſing, <hi>Ecce quàm bonum, &amp; quam jucundum eſt habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tare fratres in unum; Behold
<pb n="225" facs="tcp:170067:117"/>
how good and pleaſant a thing it is for brethren to dwell toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in unity.</hi> But whilſt you im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe upon us daily new Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of faith, and urge rigidly, what you have unadviſedly determined, we dare not Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice Truth to Peace, nor be ſeparated from the Goſpel, to be joyned to the Roman Church; Yet in the point of our ſeparation, and in all things which concern either doctrine or diſcipline, we pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs all due obedience and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to the judgement and definitions of the truly Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Church; Lamenting with all our hearts the pte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent condition of Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, which renders an Oe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumenicall Councill, if not impoſſible, (mens judgements
<pb n="226" facs="tcp:170067:118"/>
may be had, where their per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons cannot,) yet very diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult, wiſhing one, as generall as might be, and (untill God ſend ſuch an Opportunity,) endevouring to conform our ſelves in all things, both in <hi>Credendis, &amp; Agendis,</hi> to whatſoever is uniform in the belief or practiſe, in the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine or diſcipline of the U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niverſall Church; And laſtly holding an Actuall Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with all the divided parts of the Chriſtian world, in moſt things, <hi>&amp; in voto,</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to our deſires, in all things.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:170067:118"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
